<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the XI. XII and XIII. chapters of the Revellation wherein most of the matters of greatest moment contained in the booke of the Reuelation are vnfolded / by a late writer, whose certaine name is not knowne to the publisher hereof, onely these two letters T.L. are in his aduertisement to Queene Elizabeth ; the contents whereof are in the next page.</title>
            <author>T. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20075672</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20075672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1729:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the XI. XII and XIII. chapters of the Revellation wherein most of the matters of greatest moment contained in the booke of the Reuelation are vnfolded / by a late writer, whose certaine name is not knowne to the publisher hereof, onely these two letters T.L. are in his aduertisement to Queene Elizabeth ; the contents whereof are in the next page.</title>
                  <author>T. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jones?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Name of publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]¹ B-H⁸ I¹.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XI-XIII --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXPOSITION OF THE XI. XII. AND XIII. CHAPTERS OF THE REVELLATION.</p>
            <p>Wherein moſt of the matters of greateſt moment contained in the booke of the Reuelation are vnfolded.</p>
            <p>By a late Writer, whoſe certaine name <hi>is not knowne to the Publiſher hereof,</hi> onely theſe two letters <hi>T. L.</hi> are in his <hi>Aduertiſement to Queene Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Contents whereof are in the next Page.</p>
            <p>Printed An. Dom. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of theſe three Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The eſtate of the Primitiue Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her diſperſion.</item>
               <item>The Churches firſt perſecution by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>athen Emperours.</item>
               <item>The flight of the Church into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ</item>
               <item>The two Witneſſes.</item>
               <item>The riſing of Antichriſt: his ſeuen hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and ten hornes.</item>
               <item>The ſecond Beaſt, and his two hornes.</item>
               <item>The practiſe of Antichriſt and his Clergi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the Church.</item>
               <item>The Image of the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>The Marke of the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>The name and number of the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>The end of the Beaſt, and deſtruction of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Citie.</item>
               <item>And the end of the world.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The reaſons that moued me to publiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſame, are theſe two: firſt, the hope o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good that it may doe to the Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, in theſe troubleſome times: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hoping that it may be a meane to bring forth the reſt, either from the Author, or from ſome other that may haue it in keeping.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:2"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>1. The regenerate Chriſtians onely are the Church and heritage of God.</p>
               <p>3. The reſidue are outcaſts and refuſed.</p>
               <p>7. Of the two teſtifiers and preſeruers of truth.</p>
               <p>13. Antichriſt killeth them, but the Lord reſtoreth them life againe.</p>
               <p>15. Great diſſention ariſeth thereupon: the day of iudgement is foreſhewed.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VERSE 1.</hi> And there was giuen me a reed, like vnto a mete-yard; and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell that ſtood by me, ſaid, Riſe, and meaſure the Temple of God, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and them that adore therein.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in a common field, a good Surveyor doth mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out each intercommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſeuerall, by ſtake or by rod: ſo in the wide and common field of Chriſtians, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23648:3"/> Lord commandeth his ſeruant <hi>Iohn</hi> to ſurvey and apportion out his Church and partage, which he ſeuereth from the reſidue of carnall Goſpellers, and ſuch like outcaſts; in recommending vnto vs their inward frame and renewed graces, vnder the appellation and names of <hi>the Temple of God, the Altar, and them that adore therein:</hi> meaning, that as in the Tabernacle of the congregation, the holy and moſt holy places (wherein ſtood the Table of the Shew-bread, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticke, Altar of incenſe, Arke, propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory and oracle of God, ouercouered within and without with Angell-gold, into which places none but the Prieſts might enter and adore) were ſeparated by a vaile from the outer Court, where the brazen altar was erected for all the houſe of Iſrael to enter and ſacrifice, and which therefore was called the Court of the people: ſo in the common field and Vniuerſitie of Chriſtians, they onely are the Church and heritage of God, which are ſanctified in heart, and holy in life and couuerſation, and ſeparated (by the vaile of regeneration, that is to ſay, by the teares of true repentance, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23648:3"/> of pardon and reconciliation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in Chriſt Ieſus, in grauen in the tables of their hearts by the finger of the Spirit) from all carnall profeſſors and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall Chriſtians, in whom is but an outward face and proteſtation of the name of Chriſt onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 2.</bibl>
                     <p> But the baſe Court which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Temple, caſt out, and meaſure not, for it is giuen to the Gentiles: and the holy, Citie ſhall they tread vnder foot two and fortie months.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt as for thoſe common Catholique Chriſtians, here reſembled to the <hi>baſe court which is without the Temple,</hi> becauſe they are but ouercaſt onely with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of my name, which heare my word and participate my Sacraments, and yet are ſeparated by an vnregenerate heart, as by a vaile, from thoſe Altars and Prieſts, in whom my name is honored: <hi>caſt forth,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and meaſure not;</hi> for howſoeuer ſuch vnleauened compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſeeme to boaſt in the name of my Church, &amp; in the proteſtation of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23648:4"/> calling, yet they are ſo farre from belonging to my peculiar, ſaith the Lord, as that I haue giuen them vp in reckoning with the reprobate of the Gentiles, and they ſhall iuſtifie mine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and reiection of them, by their like vncircumciſed cariage and heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh conuerſation: for they ſhall no leſſe defile my holy Citie, that is to ſay, they ſhall no leſſe hate, accuſe, perſecute, and keepe vnder water the true and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Chriſtian, then do the heathen and vncircumciſed, as by ouer-long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is well knowne to the Church of God, which hath been, is, and ſhall be (till her captiuitie be returned) oppoſed for melancholy, mad, new, factious, ſchiſmaticall, hereticall, by Chriſtian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, politicians, Atheiſts, carnall Goſpellers, and ſuch heatheniſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtors like to theſe.</p>
               <p>And that the Church of God may not looke for other or better entertainment at theſe her intercommoners hands, ſhe is here (by the predeterminate counſell of God) to be troden like a way by theſe Gentiles and heatheniſh Chriſtians, two and fortie months, meaning months of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23648:4"/> yeares, euery month accounting (by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall ſupputation) thirtie yeares, as in the verſe following ſhall be further manifeſted; confounding therein the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſaries of Rome, who ſweat to perſwade that they are but months of dayes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to turne the worlds eye from the great Antichriſt that now is, to a pettie Antichriſt which ſhall neuer come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 3.</bibl>
                     <p> And I will giue to my two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and they ſhall propheſie a thouſand two hundred and ſixtie dayes cloathed in ſackcloth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>DVring which time of the Churches diſgrace &amp; deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the greater comfort of her children and iudgement of her aduerſaries, I will, ſaith the Lord; I, by a wonderfull outſtretched proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, will preſerue vnto the world the light and power of my two teſtaments, to guide their knowledge and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation into the wayes of peace. Whereby the Lord manifeſtly reproueth the groſſe and vaine expectation of thoſe that tranſlate his meaning in this place to
<pb facs="tcp:23648:5"/> the coming of <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Elias:</hi> whereas of <hi>Henochs</hi> returne, either in fleſh or in ſpirit, there is no ſyllable of promiſe in all the Scriptures; and as touching the ſpirituall returne of <hi>Elias</hi> promiſed, is already performed, as the Lord himſelfe <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 5. Mat. 11. 14</note> proueth.</p>
               <p>Now touching the time of their kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping watch while the world ſleepeth, the Lord voweth it ſhall be two and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie months before mentioned; which being diſſolued into dayes, after the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender of the Hebrewes (whoſe yeare did driue thirtie dayes to euery month, and twelue months to euery yeare) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the iuſt number of 1260 dayes here ſpecified: which computation of the yeares is obſerued throughout the whole Bible, <hi>Daniel</hi> only excepted, who counteth after the vſe and ſtile of the Caldeans, in whoſe tongue and amongſt whom he wrote; and conſequently the months being prophetical, that is to ſay, months of yeares, which to each account thirtie yeares, the reigne of Antichriſt muſt needs endure 1260 yeares. Which maner of reckoning yeares by dayes, though it ſeeme ſtrange, is vſuall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:23648:5"/> with the Prophets of God, and therefore is called Propheticall, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> a day for a yeare; and <hi>Daniels</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 4. 6. Dan. 9. 24.</note> ſeuentie weekes are weekes of yeares, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery weeke containing ſeuen yeares, as throughout this prophecie. Alſo the months are months of yeares, to euery month accounting thirtie yeares. From whence we conclude, Antichriſts three yeares and a halfe, both here and in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> deciphered by a time, times, and half a time, to be yeares of yeares, euery yeare containing twelue moneths of yeares, which amount to 360 yeares, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied by three and a halfe, do in the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall amount to 1260 yeares.</p>
               <p>And to the end the world may take better notice of theſe his two teſtifiers and preſeruers of truth, the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth the knowledge of the parties, by the deſcription of their garments, in ſaying, they are <hi>cloathed in ſackcloth;</hi> thereby not onely diſſeuering their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies from all the ſoft and courtly commentaries of fleſh and blood, which for the moſt are raiſed with infected matter, and veſted with affected ſtile; but alſo teaching vs that no man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23648:6"/> to the Lord, before whom they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, vnleſſe he ſerue in the ſame liuery that they doe, and can turne ouer the leaues of his life and pilgrimage in faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſackcloth, and true repentance, as theſe his ſeruants the Prophets and Saints haue done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 4.</bibl>
                     <p> Theſe are the two oliue branches and the two candleſticks which ſtand in the preſence of the Lord of the earth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd theſe my two Teſtaments are thoſe two oliue trees (ſaith the Lord) deſcribed by my Prophet <hi>Zechary,</hi> which ſtand and fructifie before the Ruler of the earth for euer and euer. For their leafe, that is to ſay, their word and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall neither wither nor fade, though heauen and earth ſhould periſh and melt away. And they are alſo two candleſticks, which carry in them the light of my truth, and power of my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the great moderator of heauen and earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:23648:6"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 5.</bibl>
                     <p> And if any man will hurt them, fire ſhall come forth of their mouth and deuoure their enemies; and if any man ſhall hurt them, ſo muſt he be ſlaine.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd if any man ſhal wreſt their word from the aime &amp; intention of their meaning (ſaith the Lord,) or turne their prophecie out of the way, by peruerting or clipping the honour or purpoſe of their word, the fire of my wrath denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the mouth of theſe my two teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (for though they be two, yet they haue but one mouth) ſhall ſurely iudge and execute thoſe louers and makers of lies: and for the more aſſurance of this ſentence againſt them, the Lord doth iterate the curſe and vengeance of his heauy diſpleaſure, ſaying, <hi>And if any man will hurt them, ſo muſt he be ſlaine;</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (I ſay) by hurting, all maner dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of the words of their teſtimonie by falſe, blaſphemous, and lying expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, as ſome haue done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:23648:7"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 6.</bibl>
                     <p> Theſe haue power to ſhut heauen, that it raine not in the dayes of their prophecie, and they haue power ouer the waters, to turne them into blood, and to ſmite the earth with all maner of plagues, ſo often as they will.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>FOr the Lord hath touched the mouth of theſe his two Prophets, as he did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>; mouth of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and the reſt of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, of whom he ſaith, <hi>Behold, this day haue I ſet thee ouer nations and ouer king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to plucke vp, roote out, deſtroy and throw downe, build and plant:</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, <hi>Therefore haue I cut them downe by my Prophets, and ſlaine them by the words of my mouth.</hi> Such priuiledge the Lord hath giuen to theſe his two Teſtaments, that if they once ſhut the heauens that it raine not in the dayes of their prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that is to ſay, if they denounce a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the bread of life, to wit, the word and knowledge of God; or pronounce a ſword to come vpon a nation, kingdom or people, which the Lord here ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth by turning waters into blood; or if it pleaſeth them to propheſie (which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23648:7"/> the Lord here calleth to ſtrike) of any peſtilence, earthquake, or other iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, ſuch power is giuen them, that if they ſay the word, it is done, as it is written, <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall periſh, but the words of their prophecie ſhall not paſſe, till all be fulfilled.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 7.</bibl>
                     <p> And when they ſhall haue finiſhed their teſtimonie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, the Beaſt which aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the depth, ſhall wage battell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and kill them.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd when his ſeruants the Prophets and Apoſtles ſhal haue fulfilled their courſe, and be tranſlated from the land of their labours to the land of reſt, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to the world the inheritance (as it were) of their miniſtery ſealed vp in the two Teſtaments of God, to preſerue the feare of his name and the knowledge of his pleaſure among the ſonnes of men, which the holy Ghoſt calleth <hi>finiſhing their teſtimonie;</hi> Antichriſt the Beaſt, whoſe proper place whence he is and whither he muſt, is here deſcribed by the name of the depth, ſhall not onely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23648:8"/> hurt and wound them by ſlanderous &amp; lying expoſitions, as his Clerks and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects do, but ſhall ſet his feet vpon their necks, and tread downe their diuine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie by the aduancing of his curſed keyes and the beautie of his whoriſh Church aboue them, which the Spirit calleth waging battell, inhibiting them to prophecie or teach the words of their teſtimonie vulgarly. And not onely put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to ſilence, but alſo reprouing, condemning them for corrupters, ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and ſowers of hereſies among the people; which preſumptuous blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and murder, the Spirit diſcouereth in ſaying that he ſhall ouercome them and kill them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 8.</bibl>
                     <p> And their carkeiſes ſhall remaine in the ſtreete of the great Citie, which is ſpiritually called Sodome and Egypt, where their Lord alſo was crucified.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the letter or text of their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, which the Spirit calleth their corps or carkeiſes, ſhall remaine in their houſes, Cels, Temples, hang
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23648:8"/> at their girdles through all the cities and kingdomes where the Beaſt and his Church is adored; which in regard of their number be here named <hi>the great Citie,</hi> ſo in reſpect of their execrable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and adulterous ſeruice, contrary to God and his holy Citie, they are here called alſo <hi>ſpiritually Sodome;</hi> meaning, that as Sodome her ſiſter did forſake the lawfull vſe and preſcription of nature, and wrought filthineſſe againſt nature; ſo theſe loathing truth, and louing lyes, ſhould erect ſtrange oblations and propitiations, as contrary to the offerings and ſatisfactions of the Saints, as was the ſinne of Sodome oppoſite to nature.</p>
               <p>And the Spirit further calleth them by the name of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for that in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and hardnes of heart they euery way match the preſumptuous and indurate Egyptians, ſtill purſuing and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the truth, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did Iſrael, till the God of Iſrael deſtroy them by the Spirit of his mouth, as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoaſt by water.</p>
               <p>And in further deteſtation of the cruel murder and immanitie of this Beaſt and his adherents, the holy Ghoſt layeth the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23648:9"/> blood of the Prince of the Couenant to their charge alſo, as cunningly as they thinke to conuey his murder, and poſt it ouer to Ieruſalem. For as the Lord doth lay the blood of his ſeruant <hi>Abel</hi> to the charge of the Scribes and Phariſes of his owne time, although hee were ſlaine long before thoſe Phariſes were borne or Ieruſalem builded, becauſe they were the very image and liuely imitation of his brother that murthered him: ſo the holy Ghoſt doth here lay the innocent blood of the Lord of glory to the charge of this crucifier and his citizens, becauſe they are the children and generation of that high Prieſt and thoſe murderers which cried, <hi>Away with him, crucifie him, crucifie him.</hi> And that wee ſhould not maruell thereat, the holy Ghoſt in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place goeth further, and ſaith, <hi>In her ſhall be found the blood of the Apoſtles and Prophets alſo, and all that euer for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the truth were ſlaine on earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="verse">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:23648:9"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 9.</bibl>
                     <p> And there ſhall of the tribes and people and Gentiles, ſee their dead bodies three dayes and a halfe, and ſhall not ſuffer their corps to be layed in monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd all nations and kingdoms where the Beaſt is worſhipped (whom the holy Ghoſt for their prophanation in life and religion, calleth <hi>Gentiles)</hi> ſhall haue, handle, and gaze vpon the letter and corps of his two witneſſes three days and a halfe, that is to ſay, the time, times, and halfe a time, wherein the Beaſt ſhall reigne and perſecute, euen three pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall yeares and a halfe, accounting (as in <hi>Ezekiel)</hi> all dayes for yeares. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall they ſuffer the word of their prophecie to be read, opened, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and laid vp in the hearts of the people, the true and natural monuments and ſepulchers, wherein the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of their words ought to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="verse">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:23648:10"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 10.</bibl>
                     <p> And the inhabitants of the earth ſhall be glad ouer them, and ſhall ſend gifts one to another, becauſe theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd all the worſhippers of the Beaſt here noted for their number by the inhabitants of the earth, ſhall clap their hands ouer their owne inuentions, and reioyce in the death of the truth, and make merry with bonefires, Vigils, Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uals, Proceſſions; and in token of ioy, they ſhall ſend (as the Spirit ſaith) gifts one to another. Kings and Princes and people ſhal preſent and endow the Beaſt and his Church with donations, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, poſſeſſions, gold and ſiluer offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,  and the Beaſt (on the other ſide) ſhall requite their kindneſſe with titles, bels, pardons, buls, and ſuch like: and the Spirit yeeldeth a reaſon of this their wicked and vngodly comfort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had put out the eyes of his two Prophets, that their whoredomes and prophanations might not be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; then which, nothing can be greater
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23648:10"/> torment to the wicked, nor more vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory to them that periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 11.</bibl>
                     <p> And after three dayes and a halfe the ſpirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood vpon their feete, and great feare fell vpon all that ſaw them.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd foraſmuch as in the death and extermination of Antichriſt by way of dependancie, conſiſteth the life and reſurrection (as it were) of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; the Spirit foreſheweth, that after the reigne and perſecution of the Beaſt, which here (as in the ninth verſe) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by three dayes and a half, God will raiſe vp faithfull &amp; prudent Prieſts, Shepherds of vnderſtanding hearts, who ſhall rightly diuide the words and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his two witneſſes; which the holy Ghoſt ſignifieth, in ſaying that the ſpirit of life from God entred into them: for as the letter and text of the Scripture is the corps thereof, ſo their true intent and meaning is the ſpirit and life of them; and by the faithfull miniſtery of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23648:11"/> ſuch as the Lord ſhall raiſe in and about that time, and for that purpoſe, the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of his two Prophets ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their ſtrength, and (as it were) to their walking againe, which the Spirit ſignifieth in ſaying <hi>they ſtood vpon their feete,</hi> as well to the terror and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all lying and ſtipulous expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as to the feare and admiration of the children and iuſtifiers of wiſedome, as the holy Ghoſt concludeth, ſaying, <hi>And great feare fell vpon all that ſaw them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 12.</bibl>
                     <p> And I heard a loud voice from heauen, ſaying, Come vp hither: and they went vp into heauen in a cloud, and their enemies ſaw them.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the reſtauration of the true meaning of the Scriptures, which their enemies ſo long kept vnder by all vniuſt and cunning ſhifts, ſhall be more famouſly knowne and publiſhed, then that they may any longer hinder or ſtop the glorious courſe of their wonderfull inſtauration, which the Spirit intendeth in ſaying that he <hi>heard a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23648:11"/> ſaying, Come vp hither;</hi> meaning that it ſhould be more poſſible for their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſtay <hi>Elias</hi> chariot from aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or pull the wind backe from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing his point, then to reſiſt the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the ſame, the which ſhall vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the abuſe of the Scriptures, and by the power of their miniſtery (as in the ſtrength of a cloud) ſhall hold them vp, and reſtore them to their ſpirituall and heauenly meaning againe: and the Beaſt with all his ſorcerers and liers, which haue been their long and ancient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſhall ſee the glorie of their regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and wonder, and die.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 13.</bibl>
                     <p> And in that houre there was made a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the Citie fell, and there were ſlaine in the earthquake names of men ſeuen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and the reſt were caſt into a feare, and gaue glorie to the God of heauen.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd at ſuch time as it pleaſed God to begin his worke of inſtauration, and to cauſe the dayſpring of his Goſpel to ſhine out of the night of Antichriſts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23648:12"/> darkneſſe; the abominable and deſolate prophanation of the Beaſt, which had ſo long time ouercaſt the earth, was in ſuch ſort diſcouered, that the very roote of his throne and vſurped authoritie was dangerouſly ſhaken, which the holy Ghoſt cloſely foldeth vp, in ſaying, <hi>there was made a great earthquake.</hi> And further foreſheweth, that out of this concuſſion there ſhould ariſe ſo great defection, that the tenth part of his worſhippers ſhould reuolt from him, and that this reuolt and defection muſt coſt the liues of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand men, which the Spirit vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in a maner of ſpeech ſtrange to vs, but vſuall with the Scriptures, calling men names of men, as Chap. 3. 4. and meaning by <hi>ſeuen thouſand</hi> many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, vſing the determinate number of ſeuen indefinitely and for a number in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinate, as it is alſo in Scripture of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Which broiles and bloodſhed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inſtitution of religion, are ſo ſufficiently reported in the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of Bohemia and Germanie, and in the troubles of France and Flanders, and other nations, as if it were purpoſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in proofe of this prophecie.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:23648:12"/>
               <p>Laſtly, the Spirit concluding foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that many kingdomes in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhould quite forſake the Beaſt, and haſte them out of Babylon home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to build the wals of Ieruſalem, and to reſtore the morning and the euening ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſgiuing, as in the former time and in the dayes of old, in ſaying, <hi>And the reſt were caſt into a feare, and gaue glorie to the God of heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 14.</bibl>
                     <p> The ſecond woe is gone, and behold the third woe will come quickly.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe firſt woe was the blaſphemie of Arianiſme, which the holy Ghoſt in the ninth Chapter moſt aptly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth vnto a ſmoake aſcending from the depth, ſaying, that <hi>the Sunne was darkened, and the aire with the ſmoake of the pit;</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>the Sunne</hi> the Sonne of God, and by <hi>the aire</hi> the word of his truth, by whoſe onely meane and interpoſition, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of his Deitie was truly diſcerned; and in regard of this firſt woe which was kindled by <hi>Arius,</hi> wherewith the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth (as the Spirit foretold
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23648:13"/> vs) ſhould be tormented fiue moneths, meaning moneths of yeares, which by propheticall account amounteth to one hundred and fiftie yeares, which was the time of the Arian perſecution, as in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. The holy Ghoſt, I ſay, in regard of this firſt woe, calleth the tragicall reigne of Antichriſt the ſecond woe, whoſe long time of tyrannie within this Chapter in a generall maner is declared, and in the thirteenth Chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more particularly and exactly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered; though at the writing of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, it had his being only in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of God, and was not yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to be acted, much leſſe fully ended: yet in reſpect it is here in a generall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fully reuealed, the Lord (to whom all things paſt and to come are preſent) ſaith, <hi>the ſecond woe is gone,</hi> vpon determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation whereof the third woe muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, which, for it ſurpaſſeth both the former in terror and greatneſſe, the holy Ghoſt bringeth it in with a word of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <hi>Behold, the third woe will come,</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the great and terrible day of the Lord, fore denounced by his ſeruants the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23648:13"/> Prophets, in the which all nations ſhall ſtand as priſoners before him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue euery one according to the wayes wherein their heart hath walked.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the day of the Lords co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in glorie and conſummation of the world ſhall not long tarry after the determination and conſumption of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, (as in the laſt verſe of the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter following ſhall be more fully declared) the holy Ghoſt addeth the word <hi>quickly,</hi> as a preciſe note of his ſpeedie coming, which our Lord alſo in another place confirmeth by a like word <hi>immediatly,</hi> ſaying, <hi>And immediatly after the tribulation of thoſe dayes</hi> (ſpeaking of <note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> the tyrannous reigne of the ſelfe ſame Antichriſt) <hi>they ſhall ſee the Sonne of man coming in the clouds of the aire.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 15.</bibl>
                     <p> And the ſeuenth Angell ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a Trumpet, and there were made loud voices in heauen, ſaying, The kingdomes of this world are made our Lords and his Chriſts, and he ſhal reigne for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:23648:14"/>
               <p>THe vnderſtanding of this verſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth vpon the eighth Chapter, where it is ſaid, <hi>And when he had opened the ſeuenth ſeale, there was made ſilence in heauen, &amp;c. and I ſaw ſeuen Angels ſtand in the ſight of God, and there were giuen them ſeuen trumpets &amp;c.</hi> where the holy Ghoſt meaneth by <hi>the Lamb</hi> the Sonne of God, and by opening the ſeuenth ſeale, a more particular diſcouery of all ſuch things as concerne the eſtate of his Church from his aſcenſion to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in maieſtie, diuided into ſeuen acts, declared by ſeuen trumpets, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſeuen Angels, of which acts the ſixt was the pageant of the deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Antichriſt, the ſeuenth and laſt is the coming of the Lord in the clouds of heauen, and conſummation of the world, vttered in theſe words, <hi>And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Angell ſounded with a trumpet, and with a loud voice proclaimed the kingdome of this world,</hi> ſo long time vſurped by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narks and Antichriſts, which by right of Lordſhip and inheritance, did euermore belong to the God of heauen and Prince of the Couenant, ſhall now at length be reſtored to the right Lord and lawfull
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23648:14"/> owner, and of his reigne, dominion, and glorie, there ſhall be no end, as the Spirit concludeth, ſaying, <hi>And he ſhall reigne for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 16.</bibl>
                     <p> And the foure and twenty Elders which ſate on their ſeates in the ſight of God, fell on their faces, and adoring God, ſaid, We thank thee Lord God om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, which art, which waſt, and which ſhall come, becauſe thou haſt receiued thy great power and brightneſſe.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BY the <hi>foure and twenty Elders</hi> is meant the teſtimonie of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who for that they ſpake by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fold Spirit of maieſtie which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth night and day about the throne of God, are here ſaid to ſit on their ſeates in the ſight of God. And for that their iudgements denounced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time againſt Antichriſt and his worſhippers, are now iuſtified vpon them, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting kingdome of the Lord their God (who hath ſtretched his wings from ſea to ſea, and from the Riuer to the end of lands) is now ſet vp for euermore;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23648:15"/> therefore the Spirit ſaith, that they fell on their faces, and adoring the iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, brake foorth in praiſes and thankſgiuing, ſaying, <hi>We thanke thee Lord God omnipotent, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 17.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Gentiles were angrie, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead to be iudged, and to render re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to thy ſeruants the Prophets and Saints, and to them that feare thy name, litle and great, and to deſtroy them that haue corrupted the earth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd all kingdomes, nations and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which haue euill intreated Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and made a ſport of the ſhame and affliction of Iacob, ſhal now reap the fruit of their ſauage &amp; heatheniſh liues, and (mauger their furie) ſhall endure the wrath and iudgement of him, who with iuſtice iudgeth and fighteth, as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit affirmeth, ſaying, <hi>And the Gentiles were angrie, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead to be iudged.</hi> And the Spitit further teſtifieth, that the Lord (for whoſe glorie that day is made) ſhall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23648:15"/> to euery one their due hire or wages, (for ſo the originall importeth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly interpreted <hi>reward,)</hi> firſt to his Saints and ſeruants, and all that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, their hire and wages, which by promiſe and for his owne name ſake is due vnto them; next, to all execrable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, blaſphemous Catholiques, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous heathen, liers, heretiques, carnall Goſpellers, and all other brazen and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Chriſtians, the hire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which to their works, and deeds, and merits is due, as the Spirit concludeth, ſaying, <hi>And to render reward vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the Prophets and Saints, and to them that feare thy name, little and great, and to deſtroy them that haue corrupted the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But concerning this ſeuenth age, wherein the Lord ſhall come in maieſtie to iudge the quicke and the dead, the holy Ghoſt deferreth yet a while to ſpeak more particularly thereof, and reſumeth more exactly to intreat of the terme and perſecution of Antichriſt and his accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices againſt the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt, that ſo the glory of his iuſtice in their iuſt condemnation and iudgement may be more bright and manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>1. A confirmation of the prophecie follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>2. The deſcription of the Church and of her firſt fruit.</p>
               <p>4. The Churches firſt perſecution raiſed by Ethnicke Rome, by whoſe immanitie it came to paſſe that her beautie was no more ſeene in her viſible and eminent graces, but liued here and there diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſcattered ouer the face of the earth.</p>
               <p>8. The great battell betweene Chriſtianiſme and Paganiſme: Chriſt and his truth ouercommeth Iupiter and his prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>18. The Empire remoueth his Throne, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſtop the floate of the enemie, but intending to roote out the diſperſed remnant of the Church.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:23648:16"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 1.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Temple of God was opened in heauen, and the Arke of his Couenant was ſeene in his Temple, and there was made lightnings, voices, thunders, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, and great haile.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Apoſtle hauing drawne in the former part of this prophecie a ſlight draught (as it were) and deſignement of Antichriſt, doth now in the prophecie following reviſit and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the diſcouery of the Beaſt, and hang him vp to the view and diſcerning of heauen and earth. And to the end that this his work of manifeſtation may carry in it faire and vncontrollable credit, the Apoſtle in this verſe aſſureth vs, that he reuealeth no other word concerning the Church &amp; her preſſours here on earth, during the perſonal abſence of her Lord, then that which he heard at the Councel table of God, which he deliuereth in a maner of ſpeech vſuall with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>And the Temple of God was opened in heauen, and the Arke of his couenant was ſeene in the Temple,</hi> alluding to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ieruſalem, and ſignifying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>under,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23648:17"/> that the words of this his Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are no leſſe ſooth and true, then if he had receiued them from the Oracle of God, which ſpake from ouer the Arke of his teſtament within the Temple of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, whoſe words and anſwers, for their diuinitie, maieſtie, power and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, are here as elſewhere figured by voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces proper to God, and not to man, as <hi>lightnings, thunders, earthquakes, and haile.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 2.</bibl>
                     <p> And a great ſigne appeared in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, a woman cloathed with the Sunne, and the Moone vnder her feete, and on her head a crowne of twelue ſtarres.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt before the Spirit takes in hand to diſcouer the perſecuters of the Church, it pleaſeth him firſt to deſcribe the Church it ſelfe, that ſo the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous immanitie of her enemies may be more apparent and iuſtly abhorred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vſed againſt a creature of ſuch virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, innocent and patient modeſtie, who for her rare and admirable beauty is here called <hi>a great ſigne,</hi> or heauenly appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſymbolizing her fearfull, modeſt, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23648:17"/> and matronlike behauiour, with the appellation and qualitie of a woman; for ſo ſhe is in holy Scriptures often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the faireſt woman, the Kings daughter, daughter of Sion, daughter of Ieruſalem, the Spouſe of Chriſt, Mother of the iuſt, &amp;c.</hi> And to the end ſhe may the better be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned of vs, the Apoſtle deſcribeth her garments and wearing, ſaying, ſhe was <hi>cloathed with the Sun,</hi> meaning that ſhe had put on the Lord Ieſus, Sonne of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that is to ſay, her ſoule was veſted with an aſſurance of the mercie and loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus her Lord; which iuſtice or iuſtification of the Spouſe and her children, is called in holy Scripture by way of metaphor, <hi>the white ſtone,</hi> and <hi>the wedding garment.</hi> For as a ſtoale or gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment couereth the ſhame and nakednes of our vile bodies: ſo the mercy and loue of God, inſured vs in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, hideth the ſhame and nakedneſſe of our ſinfull ſoules. And to proue that her garment was truly wouen of the two diuine threds, to wit, the aſſurance of mercie &amp; the aſſurance of loue in Chriſt Ieſus her Lord; the Spirit giueth in for euidence, the fruits of this her liuely and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23648:18"/> iuſtificall faith, cloſely hiding her new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, her hatred of ſinne, and her loue of God, as vnder a vaile, in theſe words, <hi>And the Moone vnder her feet;</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thereby that ſhe had now quite forſaken &amp; forgotten her fathers houſe, that is, had ſlaine her naturall ſinfull and wonted affections, and was reuiued and renewed in mind, and with her Lord was now riſen and aſcended vp, as he into the heauen of heauens, ſo ſhe to a new cuſtome and cariage of life, far aboue and higher then the Moone: for all her ſtudy and hearts delight was now in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where her hope, her loue, her life, and her deareſt Lord liueth &amp; reigneth, God, to be praiſed for euer and euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, the Spirit ſetteth forth her head attire, whereby her honour and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate was beſt knowne, and wherein ſhe moſt delighted, ſaying, that ſhe wore on her head a crowne made of a mettall much finer then gold, for it was made of the doctrine of the twelue Apoſtles, who for that they are the Lords lights and lanternes to guide the feet of ſinners when ſinne hath benighted them, are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23648:18"/> here called by the names of Starres, <hi>And on her head a crowne of twelue ſtarres.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 3.</bibl>
                     <p> And being great with child, ſhe cried, trauelling and labouring to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd by the words which her eares receiued, her heart conceiued, and ſhe was great with feare and godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, trauelling vnder the burthen of her ſinnes, and reſtleſſe deſire to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to God: which anguiſh and paines of her ſorrowful heart and broken ſpirit, the Apoſtle moſt excellently compareth to the ſorrowes of a woman in trauell. In which her ſpiritual labour and paine, ſhe could by no meanes be relieued or eaſed, vntill her Lord were faſhioned in her, that is, vntill her heart were ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by faith: for no Treacle could heale her miſerable wounded ſoule, but the aſſurance of mercie onely, nor any water could quench the burning flames of her reſtleſſe deſire, but the loue of God onely, inſured her in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus her Lord, and written in the fleſhly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:23648:19"/> tables of her heart by the finger of God, according to his promiſe, his firſt and laſt and euerlaſting couenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 4.</bibl>
                     <p> And another ſigne appeared in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for loe a great red Dragon hauing ſeuen heads and ten hornes, and on his heads ſeuen diadems.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AS night doth follow day, and the ſhadow the body; ſo muſt the Croſſe follow Chriſt, and affliction his Church; whoſe Sunne could no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhine, but the enuious man raiſed vp a mightie ſtorme of perſecution to cloud the brightneſſe of her beautiful beames; which for the extraordinary furie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Apoſtle calleth <hi>a wonder</hi> or <hi>ſigne,</hi> meaning the Churches firſt and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue perſecution raiſed by Ethnik Rome, who for his power, immanitie and malice to the Church of God, is here called <hi>a great red Dragon;</hi> and both for that his Throne and Citie was ſeated on ſeuen hils; as alſo for that he was in all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie, pride and prophanation, the totall ſumme and epitome (as it were) of all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23648:19"/> the ſeuen Monarchies, vnto whom (from the beginning of time, to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) was giuen and granted the charter and commiſſion of blaſpheming God &amp; corrupting his world (as in the thirteenth Chapter following is more particularly diſcouered) the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>hauing ſeuen heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in regard his power did beate down the power of all nations, and made ſpoile and purchaſe of all kings &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes on earth, the Spirit ſaith, he had <hi>ten hornes:</hi> for the hornes ſignifie kings and kingdomes, and the number of <hi>ten</hi> include all, be they neuer ſo many, as all numbers are made of ten, and their redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, be they neuer ſo infinite.</p>
               <p>And becauſe he came to aduance his head ſo high by the power of his ſword, his Leaders and legions, the Spirit crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his heads with magnificence and diadems, ſaying, <hi>And on his heads ſeuen diadems.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 5.</bibl>
                     <p> And his taile drew the third part of the ſtarres of heauen, and caſt them to the earth. And the Dragon ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23648:20"/> the woman which was ready to be deliuered, that when ſhe had brought forth, he might deuoure her ſonne.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe head of this great red Dragon, was his Regall firſt eſtate, gouerned by <hi>Romulus</hi> &amp; ſix other ſucceſſiue king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coates, which <hi>Seneca</hi> calleth his infancie or nonage, wherein he liued ſwathed and nouriſhed in blood 244 yeares, as his owne Hiſtorian reporteth.</p>
               <p>The bodie of this great red Dragon, was his Conſuls ſecond eſtate, which <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> calleth his full age, part Ariſtocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, part Democraticall, and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtiled, <hi>Senatus populuſque Romanus:</hi> from whence partly by reaſon of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerweight and fulſome abundance, as one of his owne noteth, <hi>Romana laxitas mundi &amp; rerum amplitudo damno fuit;</hi> and partly for want of enemies abroad to wreake their proud and kingly humours on, he fell into the inteſtine euill of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warres at home, which did caſt him into his minoritie and wardſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>And this his laſt eſtate of regiment Imperiall, the holy Ghoſt here calleth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23648:20"/> 
                  <hi>his taile,</hi> which conſiſteth of a rout of Monarchs, ſeuentie Keyſars long, who for that they ſo furiouſly perſecuted and hauocked the blood of the chiefeſt Saints and ſeruants of God, the Spirit ſaith that with his curſed <hi>taile he drew the third part of the ſtarres of heauen, and caſt them to the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not contented with the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his faireſt lights and ſtarres of his Church, proceeded to deſolate the whole hoaſt of heauen, euen all the ſeed of the Spouſe, named before the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches child, and here <hi>her ſonne,</hi> meaning thoſe in whom by the miniſtery of his faireſt ſtarres (his ſeruants the Apoſtles) Chriſt was now formed, and of whom the Church was now ready to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered; for ſo much the Apoſtle vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in theſe words, <hi>And the Dragon ſtood before the woman which was ready to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, that when ſhe ſhould bring forth, he might deuoure her ſonne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 6.</bibl>
                     <p> But ſhe brought forth a man child, who was to gouerne all nations in an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23648:21"/> rod: and her ſon was taken vp to God and to his throne.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt notwithſtanding all their furie, the Church brought forth her firſt fruit, which for their faith, charitie, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and patience, the Spirit nameth <hi>a man child:</hi> and becauſe they followed the Lord in the regeneration, and ouercame by keeping his words and works vnto the end, they receiued the ſelfe ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which to their Lord alone and in chiefe belongeth, namely, that they ſhall <hi>iudge the Tribes of Iſrael, and haue dominion ouer the nations, and ſhall rule them with a rod of iron, and breake their glorie like a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters veſſell,</hi> as the Lord hath promiſed, Math. 19. and Apoc. 2.</p>
               <p>And in remembrance of the tender care and prouidence of God ouer the ſeed and firſt fruit of his Church, the Spirit concludeth, that when they had ended their courſe, <hi>they were taken vp to God and to his throne,</hi> far from the reach and rage of their enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:23648:21"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 7.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Woman fled into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, where ſhe had a place prepared of God, that there they might feed her a thouſand two hundred and ſixtie dayes.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt the Church of God, here named <hi>the woman,</hi> mother of this faire and primitiue fruit, being no longer able to weather out her ſtormes, was enforced to hide her beautie, and to retire her ſelfe into the ſecret chambers of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and her owne conſcience, and to take vp her lodging in the deſart; not that her light was vtterly extinguiſhed, as her enemies reproch her: for although ſhe were diſperſed, diſtreſſed, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to hide her extraordinary and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent graces; yet the beautie of her true repentance and of her liuely faith, ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a charitable life and patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of better things to come, ſtill ſhined as a candle in a darke place; and like a ſhip preſerued in a tempeſt, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtil the ſame, of whom the world was not worthy; neuer wanting the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing protection of her deareſt Lord,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23648:22"/> who in all her troubles was mindfull of her, as of <hi>Elias</hi> his ſeruant, or Iſrael his firſt borne; carefull to prouide her both of honorable harbour and princely diet. Her reſting place was reſtleſſe, ſtrewed and ſcattered far and neare ouer the face of the earth; for ſuch a lodging did beſt beſeeme her broken and reſtleſſe heart, which ſoiourned in earth, but dwelt in heauen; and did alſo beſt defend her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the furious inquiſitions of her enemies.</p>
               <p>Neither was her Lord leſſe louing and prouident concerning her food, for he preſerued for her diet the two witneſſes of his eternall Couenant, that from their breaſt ſhe might ſucke the pure and wholeſome milke of grace and life, that ſo ſhe might be both nobly harboured and princely fed during the tedious and odious reigne of the great Whore the Church of Rome, who during her exile ſhould vſurpe her Chaire, and vnder the vizard of her name ſhould perſecute her name and generation <hi>a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixtie yeares,</hi> here (as before) my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically deciphered vnder <hi>a thouſand two hundred and ſixtie dayes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:23648:22"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 8.</bibl>
                     <p> And there was waged a battell in heauen, Michael and his Angels fought with the Dragon; and the Dragon fought, and his Angels.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd at the ſame time that the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God was opened in heauen, the Apoſtle alſo foreſaw that great and bloody contention, then which (ſince the dayes of heauen) was neuer waged greater; great in regard of the armies, and great in reſpect of the cauſe.</p>
               <p>The armies great, as well for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Generals, as for the valour and number of their forces.</p>
               <p>The Generall on the one ſide, was the power of God, ſciphered by <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince of the Couenant, who ſtood for the children and people of the Higheſt. The Generall on the other ſide, was the power of Satan, figured by Ethnicke Rome, here (as before) called <hi>the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In their forces are to be conſidered the Leaders and the ſouldiers. The Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and the Captains on the part of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> were <hi>Diuus Petrus, Diuus Paulus,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23648:23"/> Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Iohannes,</hi> and the reſt of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and noble order of Saints. And on the Dragons part were Leaders and Chieftaines, <hi>diuus Tiberius, diuus Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, diuus Claudius, diuus Nero,</hi> and the reſt of that moſt filthy and execrable traine.</p>
               <p>So great was the multitude and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſouldiers, that none of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, ſex, age, or condition ſoeuer, but muſt be preſt for the one ſide or for the other; the valour and vertue of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers exceeded all praiſe; few ſubdued many, the weake ouercame the ſtrong, a handfull of Chriſtians a world of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</p>
               <p>The cauſe was great, and higher then the heauens; whether God or Belial, Chriſt or Iupiter, Chriſtianiſme or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme were more venerable for anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, maieſticall for amplitude, more conſtant for continuance, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpects of wiſedome, honour and maieſtie more worthy to be embraced and adored of the ſonnes of men; which was for life contended by the Dragon, his Angels and aſſects, and was for life withſtood and diſapproued by <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, and their followers.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23648:23"/> The iſſue of this contention followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 9.</bibl>
                     <p> But they preuailed not, neither was their place found any more in heauen.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AS the battell was great, ſo was the victory glorious: for though the Dragon with his ſapient Senates, his prophane Angels, and his vncleane ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors, intended all their forces, mouing (as it is in prouerb) heauen and earth to make roome for the abomination of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and to keepe vnder water the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting Lord and Prince of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; as among the many monuments of time is ſufficiently proued and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by <hi>Oroſius,</hi> and by him to whom he wrote in his booke <hi>de Ciuitate Dei;</hi> yet the Spirit foreſeeing the Dragons folly, and how in vaine he kickt againſt the ſpurre, in ſcorne of his preſumption ſaith, <hi>But he preuailed not;</hi> and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding affirmeth, that the poſſeſſion of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (ſo long time vſurped by inceſtuous murtherers, and execrable curtizans, gods and goddeſſes of their owne forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) muſt be reſigned now to the true
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23648:24"/> Lord and owner of all, who hath taken his place at the right hand of the Father, and hath depoſed for euer from their v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped titles of deitie, all gods and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes, phantaſmes made of wormes, created and diuified by the inuentions, relations, conſecrations, and canonizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Dragon, his Taile and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as the Spirit diſcouereth in ſaying, <hi>Neither the place of them was found any more in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 10.</bibl>
                     <p> And that great Dragon was throwne downe, the old Serpent, called the Diuell and Satanas, which ſeduceth the whole world, and he was caſt into the earth, and his Angels were throwne downe with him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the great and prophane power of the Romane monarchie, which had ſo long time oppreſſed and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the earth, was now at length detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thereupon diſſeized of, and from her vſurped claime of heauen for euer, as the Spirit diſcouereth in ſaying, <hi>And that great Dragon was throwne downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:23648:24"/>
               <p>And for that the diuell did corporally dwell (as it were) in her, ſpreading the beames of his wickedneſſe at full, in all idolatrie, impietie and preſumption a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and in all oppreſſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and immanitie towards man; the Spirit crowneth her with the cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of her ſire, calling her, for her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to the truth, a <hi>Serpent;</hi> for her crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints, a <hi>diuell;</hi> and for hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to God and his Saints, <hi>Satanas:</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therein after the maner of the Lord himſelf, who calleth his trecherous ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard <hi>a diuel,</hi> thogh he were a man, becauſe the fulneſſe of Satan did dwel in him, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his heart with ſuch a perfect hatred of his innocent Lord, &amp; lamentable loue of his guiltie penie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſold Canaan for Egypt, heauen for hell, &amp; God for ſiluer.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the impietie of gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, is not onely their owne decay by euill doing, but alſo by enforcement and euill example the ruine of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the Spirit layeth the ſeduction of the whole earth to the charge of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, for the ruling it after the leuell and preſcription of Rome, ſaying, <hi>which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the whole world;</hi> and thereupon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23648:25"/> iuſt iudgement and ſentence of death againſt him, namely, that as in his beginning he crept out of the earth, and by the ſcale of his wickedneſſe aſcended ſo high, as to preſume to thruſt his haughtie head into heauen, and build his neaſt aboue the ſtarres, as did his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teceſſors, <hi>Aſſur, Beltaſſar, Darius, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and the reſt of their compeeres: ſo by a like power of ſword and crueltie, he ſhall ſhortly returne to his friends again, and be made euen with the earth, from whence his ſtocke and firſt eſtate was borrowed; and the power of his Ceſars, councell of his Senators, ſophiſtrie of his Sorcerers (which with ſuch indurate and obſtinate mindes ſtood for the honour and worſhip of diuels) ſhould be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to vphold the reuerence of their <hi>Iupiter Capitolinus,</hi> who was now detec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a rogue, and by the voices of <hi>Michaels</hi> Angels (as by whips and paſports) was ſent home againe to the place of his birth, namely the earth, from whence his mortall and vile genealogie was taken, and with him alſo were Ceſars vndiuified, and (for all their Senates proud relations) were made
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23648:25"/> to take vp the graue for their latter end, and ſhame for their fame, and wormes for their heritage, as the Spirit foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſaying, <hi>And he was caſt downe vnto the earth, and his Angels were throwne downe with him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 11.</bibl>
                     <p> And I heard a great voice in heauen, ſaying, Now is made ſaluation, and force, and kingdome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt, becauſe the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of our brethren is caſt downe, who accuſed them before the ſight of our God day and night.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NEither was this famous victorie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a corner, or ſpoken in the eare, but (as the Spirit reporteth) ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorouſly gotten, and ſo audibly proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that all the world heard the report thereof, witneſſe the records of thoſe times, at which the holy Ghoſt pointeth in theſe words, <hi>And I heard a loud voice in heauen, ſaying,</hi> and ſounding the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſt and Chriſtianiſme againſt the Dragon and his Angels, his ſorcerers and their prophane and idolatrous paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23648:26"/> in theſe deuout &amp; diuine notes, <hi>Now is made ſaluation, and force, and the kingdome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt;</hi> and yeeldeth a reaſon of this ſo pious and triumphant ioy, becauſe the folly and fury of the Dragon and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which ſo continually accuſed the Saints and ſeruants of God, for peſtilent fellowes, mouers of ſedition, maintainers of ſects, polluters of the Temple, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of new gods, enemies to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſowers, babblers, blaſphemers, is now vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſetting and going downe for euer. Which death and downfall of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall whoredome, the holy Ghoſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſeth, in ſaying, <hi>becauſe the accuſer of our brethren is caſt forth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the greater comfort of the Church and iudgement of her enemies, concludeth, that there is a perfect court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roule kept, as wel of the ſufferings of the Saints, as of the ſlanders of their foes, ſo openly committed in the face of the Court, and before a Iudge of ſo cleare a ſight and eternall memory, as that they ſhall neuer be diſcharged or forgotten, the Spirit inferreth, ſaying, <hi>who accuſed them before the ſight of our God day &amp; night.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="verse">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:23648:26"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 12.</bibl>
                     <p> And they ouercame him by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of their teſtimonie; and they loued not their liues euen vnto the death.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>LAſt of all the holy Ghoſt diſcouereth the ſpirituall armour and weapons wherewith the Angels and ſeruants of <hi>Michael</hi> obtained this famous victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Dragon and his ſectaries, and ſaith, that they were tempered of theſe two diuine vertues, faith and patience. For by the ſhield of faith, which the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (by a metonymie) calleth, <hi>the blood of the Lamb,</hi> and with the ſword of his two witneſſes, and by the word of their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, they ouerthrew all forces and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments drawn from reaſon or reading, which the Spirit obſerueth in theſe words, <hi>And they ouercame him by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie,</hi> and all ſuch arguments as were drawne from the blocke, as fire, ſword, perſecution, interdiction, and ſuch like, the children of the Church quenched them with teares, prayers, patience and martyrdome, as their Lord had giuen them charge, and left them example;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:23648:27"/> which the Spirit vncouereth in ſaying, <hi>And they loued not their liues euen vnto the death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 13.</bibl>
                     <p> Therefore reioyce O heauens, and you that dwell in them. Woe to the earth and to the ſea, becauſe the diuell is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to you, hauing great wrath, knowing that he hath but a little time.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AS after victory followeth diuiſion of ſpoile, ſo the Spirit ſhuts vp this heauenly conqueſt with triumph and ioy, inuiting thereunto all the Saints and ſeruants of God, which haue from time to time maintained and defended the honour of his name againſt the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, his ſorcerers and ſorceries. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by their good profeſſion and godly conuerſation they teſtified the glorie of God (as doe the heauens) by their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent conuerſions, the Spirit crowneth them with the name of the heauens, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Therefore reioyce O heauens, and you that dwell in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And on the other part, pronounceth <hi>woe,</hi> firſt to all nations and kingdomes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23648:27"/> acceſſary to theſe ſpirituall whoredomes of the Dragon, whom (according to their earthly mind) he moſt aptly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth to the earth; next, to the Empire it ſelfe, as the <hi>ſcelerum caput</hi> and ſtable of iniquitie, whom for his fearfull power and vnbridled rage, the Spirit moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly calleth by the name of <hi>the Ocean</hi> and <hi>the ſea:</hi> and concludeth his <hi>woe</hi> with a reaſon why, becauſe both in one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the power of Satan had taken ſuch deepe roote, that the more the light of the truth did bewray their madneſſe, the more they ſtroue and ſtormed againſt it; and ſo much the rather, becauſe their ſinne was now at the higheſt; and that the kingdome of Chriſt did gather ſo faſt vpon them, that of neceſſity a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their fortunes muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, with a ſubuerſion not onely of their Paganiſme, but alſo of their power Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall, which the Spirit cloſely foldeth vp in theſe words, <hi>Knowing that he hath but a little time;</hi> which one Apoſtle alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, 2. Theſſ. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="verse">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:23648:28"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 14.</bibl>
                     <p> And when the Dragon ſaw that he was throwne to the earth, he perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the woman that brought forth the man child.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd when the raging Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ſaw that his maintenance of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and his idol art of making ſhrines was to deſcend for euer, (as among many voices, ſome euen to this day are heard to crie vengeance vpon his idols, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them with ſhame to reſigne their vſurped titles of gods and claime of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the true Lord and owner thereof) he took the courſe of the wicked, whoſe cuſtome is (as one of their owne noteth) <hi>malitia alia aliam trudere,</hi> and to adde ſin to ſin, (as a holy one ſaith) to quench his <note place="margin">Deut. 29.</note> thirſt with drunkenneſſe: for ſo procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this Beaſt, adding to his blindneſſe boldneſſe, redeeming his blaſphemie with rage and perſecution; and was ſo far from coming to himſelfe, and taking vp repentance to waſh away his crying ſinnes, that (as the Spirit concludeth) he more and more purſued the Church, &amp; perſecuted the woman which brought
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23648:28"/> forth her firſt borne and primitiue fruit, here called for their faith, their patience, and their godly valour <hi>the man child.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 15.</bibl>
                     <p> And there was giuen vnto the woman two wings of the great Eagle, that ſhe might flie into the deſart, vnto her place, where ſhe was nouriſhed for a time, and times, and halfe a time, from the face of the Serpent.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt the Lord, who had ſo dearly bought his Shunamite, was no leſſe carefull to preſerue and carry her to the place of her reſt, with a ſtrong and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched prouidence, euen vpon his owne two wings, whoſe feathers were made of the truth of his promſe, ſealed and deliuered by the hand of his two witneſſes, which the Bridegroom of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe left with his Spouſe, to accompanie and guide her whenſoeuer ſhe remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. If ſhe trauell by day, they are her leading cloud; if by night, they are her pillar of fire: if ſhe flie, they lend her wings; if ſhe wander, they harbour her; if ſhe be naked, they couer her; if in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:23648:29"/> they viſit her; if captiue, they redeem her; if ſhe be weake, they ſuſtaine her; if blind, they leade her; if ſhe be heauie, they comfort her; if ſicke, they recouer her; if ſhe doubt, they reſolue her; if ſhe erre, they direct her: if ſhe thirſt, they giue her to drinke; and if ſhe hunger, they feed her, and make her ſo ſtrong of conſtitution, that afflictions are reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings to her, baniſhment a hauen, diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a friend, loſſe and death aduantage. And by theſe comforts (as by hands) they conuey her to her ſolitude and reſtleſſe place of reſt, as the Spirit diſcouereth, ſaying, <hi>But there were giuen to the woman two wings of the great Eagle, that ſhe might flie into the deſart, vnto her reſting place,</hi> where euer ſince her primitiue diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhe hath liued ſtrewed and ſcattered far and neare ouer the face of the earth, ſeene and knowne of her Lord, by whom ſhe is protected, and of the children of wiſedome, of whom ſhe is iuſtified: and ſo doth and muſt remaine hidden and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into the priuie chambers of Gods prouidence and her owne conſcience, during the reigne of Antichriſt, whoſe curſt and arrogant ſupremacy was to riſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23648:29"/> out of the aſhes of the Dragons Emperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie, as the holy Ghoſt prophecied.</p>
               <p>And thus, hiding her eminent primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue graces, muſt cloſely and ſilently keep the Lords watch, and ſtand vpon her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable guard three propheticall yeares and a halfe, here (as in <hi>Daniel)</hi> determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a time, and times, and half a time, from the reach and rage of the Serpent, his taile and ſucceſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 16.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Serpent caſt out of his mouth, after the woman, water, as it were a flood, that he might make her to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with the flood.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd when the Dragons traine of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars (who for their malice to the truth, and ſeducing the nations, are here called by the name of the ancient enemy and ſeducer of mankind <hi>the Serpent)</hi> ſaw that they could no longer hauocke the Church of God, by reaſon of her cloſe ſight and ſecret diſperſion, they deuiſed to purſue her with their bloody edicts and ſacrilegious conſtitutions, which they breathed out againſt her in ſuch
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23648:30"/> raging and furious maner, as the Spirit therefore reſembleth the violence of their barbarous inquiſitions and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>princely reſcripts vnto the vnmercifull rage and current of a flood, hoping that as by their vnplacable furie they had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and driuen the Spouſe to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo by the due execution of their cruell promulgations they might vtterly conſume her generation, and blot out all letters of her honorable name; for to that white onely they aimed, as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit concludeth, <hi>That he might make her to be caried away of the flood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 17.</bibl>
                     <p> And the earth holp the Woman, and the earth opened her mouth, and ſwallowed vp the flood which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BVt in reliefe of the Churches preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and perſecutions, her Lord gaue charge vnto his handmaide the earth, to comfort, help and ſuccour her his Spouſe: and as Moab was charged to hide the chaſed Iſrael of God, and not bewray him that was fled and eſcaped,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23648:30"/> but to dwell with him, and to giue him couert and protection from the face of the deſtroyer; ſo here the earth was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to reach forth her helping hand, and to take in and harbour the Lords ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles, in the ſeret chambers of her deſarts, mountaines and caues, that ſo ſhe might either affoord her cloſe and quiet ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, or in witneſſe of her faith and proofe of her patience, receiue the blood which her curſed brethren ſpilt; which courteſie and tender fauour, the Spirit remembreth to the perpetuall praiſe of the benefactors of the Spouſe, ſaying, <hi>But the earth holp the Woman, and opened her mouth, and ſwallowed vp the flood which the Dragon caſt out of his mouth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 18.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Dragon was wroth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Woman, and went to make battell with the remnant of her ſeed, which keepe the commandements of God, and haue the teſtimonie of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd notwithſtanding the Dragon by his taile of <hi>Ceſars</hi> had thus maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred and diſperſed the Church, yet
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23648:31"/> was he not ſo ſatisfied, but for very rage fell into a melancholy mood, for cauſe he could not quite conſume and roote her honour out, as the Spirit diſcloſeth, ſaying, <hi>And the Dragon was wroth againſt the Woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as the Churches beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie did moſt ſhine in the Eaſt Syria, Greece, Aſia, where ſhe was borne and bred, the Dragon thought it his beſt (in policie, which euermore with him was held for chiefeſt religion) to itch and ſet forward his den, and hold his Court fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eaſt; which purpoſe of his, as cloſe as it was, the holy Ghoſt diſcouereth, in ſaying, <hi>And he went;</hi> and noteth the true end wherefore he went, not ſo much to barricade and ſtop the floate and incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the barbarous enemie, as he (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) pretended, as to purſue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the diſperſed remainder of the Spouſe, as the Spirit vnfoldeth, ſaying, <hi>to make battell with the remnant of her ſeed,</hi> who for that they were iuſt of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and growth of the Churches firſt and primitiue fruite, holding the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of faith in a good conſcience, as the firſt borne did, the Spirit ſetteth them
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:23648:31"/> forth in the ſame liuely colours, ſaying, <hi>which keepe the commandements of God, and haue the teſtimonie of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 19.</bibl>
                     <p> And he ſtood vpon the ſand of the ſea.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the Drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remoued his throne, and left his ancient ſeate and citie of Rome, where he had now kept court almoſt a thouſand yeares, and went and pitched his throne anew in a hauen towne, betweene Pontus Euxinus and Propontis in the Eaſt of Thracia, anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently called Byſance, and there erected the new citie of Rome, and called it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne name Conſtantinople the citie of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> which tranſlation of his reſidence and chaire of eſtate, one of his owne alſo noteth:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſtantinus apud Thraces, qua Boſphorus aequor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thracius Euxinis Aegaeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ingurgitat vndis, conſtituit ſedem Imperij.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:23648:32"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The deſcription of Antichriſt, and his deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</p>
               <p>The deſcription of his Cleargie and of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>The Character of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>The number of his dayes, and the end of his reigne.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 1.</bibl>
                     <p> And I ſaw a Beaſt aſcending from the ſea, hauing ſeuen heads and ten hornes, and vpon his hornes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ten dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems, and vpon his heads names of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd preſently vpon the remoue and tranſlation of the Empire, the Apoſtle eſpied that wicked one, Antichriſt, man of ſinne, in ſaying, <hi>And I ſaw;</hi> who in regard of the tyrannous power and bloody vſe of the vnbridled
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23648:32"/> iuriſdiction that ſhould be giuen him, he is here termed (as in holy Scriptures other Monarchs are) <hi>A Beaſt,</hi> that is to ſay, a kind of gouernment, kingdome, dominion or power exerciſed and acted by a ſucceſſion of tyrannous, bloody and beaſtly men.</p>
               <p>And albeit his perfection in euill ſtood yet aloofe, and was very farre off, yong and tender, as lying in ſwathing clouts; yet the Apoſtle deſcrieth him, as it were through a chinke, in ſaying, <hi>coming vp.</hi> For after the tranſlation of the Empire, and that now Ethnicke Rome began to play the Chriſtian, he was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh a hundred yeares cloſely creeping and climing vp, before he could aduance his curſed head and claime of ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie. Concerning which ambitious puffe of vaine prioritie, ſo faire and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mention is made in the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of time, that the incredible bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the aduerſarie is no leſſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous then his incurable blindneſſe, that hath ſo long time ſtumbled at this ſtone, and ſo often ſpurred vs by way of vaunting, to ſhew them (if we dare or can) when this apoſtacie of Antichriſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:23648:33"/> tooke her riſe and firſt commencement: which daring vaunt of theirs, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt tripping ouer as a thing which is or ought to be knowne vnto vs, namely, that the horne of Antichriſt and his apoſtacie did then firſt ſprout out, when his Church firſt obtained at the Dragons hand prioritie of place, ſuffrage and cenſure ouer all. For as the tree puls vp the creeping ivie, ſo the primacie of the Church of Rome pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp the aſpiring ſupremacie of the Biſhop thereof; which Church prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and prelation (after long ruffling and ſhouldring) was firſt obtained at the hands of <hi>Honorius</hi> (though afterwards vpon greater concertation and daggers drawing, it was by other Ceſars and Kings confirmed, renewed and amplia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) who by the aduantage of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death of his elder brother <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius,</hi> hauing obtained power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectorſhip Eaſt and Weſt, ſubiected the Church of the Eaſt Empire (which moſt withſtood the Weſt and Romane ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie) with all other Churches whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, to the Church and Sea of Rome, at the inſtant ſuit and importunitie of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23648:33"/> now Biſhop of Rome, whoſe name was then <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt, in the firſt yeare of his creation, and in the yeare of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption 406.</p>
               <p>But the holy Ghoſt (I ſay) paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the punctuall and exact moment of time, when the egge of Antichriſt and his Apoſtacie was firſt laid, as otherwhere ſufficiently preſerued vnto vs, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to detect the place where and from whence he ſhould ariſe, ſaying, that he ſaw him lift vp his hardy head <hi>from the ſea,</hi> meaning <hi>by the ſea,</hi> as in the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of this prophecie, the ſurging, tumbling and raging Sea and Citie of Rome, where alſo by a like loquution he calleth all kingdoms ſubiected to her by the name of <hi>riuers.</hi> And that this Beaſt ſhould thence ariſe, and there (and not elſewhere) keep court and reſidence, the Spirit proueth by an argument drawne from the ſhape and proportion of the Beaſt, for he had the ſeuen heads and ten hornes of the Dragon, meaning that he ſhould ſit vpon the Dragons hils, and reigne in and ouer the Dragons ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and aray himſelfe with the ſpoiles of the world, and hold in ſubiection the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23648:34"/> Kings and States on earth, as the Dragon did; for ſo much the Spirit intendeth in ſaying, <hi>hauing ſeuen heads and ten hornes.</hi> And leſt the vnwary Reader ſhould miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this great Antichriſt for that great Dragon, or this Beaſts ſupremacie and his peſtilent ſucceſſion for that Beaſts ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminencie and his execrable taile (as many vnwarily haue done,) the holy Ghoſt in emblazoning his coate, giueth him a moſt exquiſite difference, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he wore his <hi>diadems,</hi> not vpon his heads, as the Dragon did, but vpon his hornes; ſignifying thereby that he ſhould not come to his Crowne and vainglory by the ſtrength of his ſword, his Leaders and his legions, as the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon did, but by the baſe and voluntary ſubmiſſion of all ſuch Ceſars, Kings and Princes as ſhould with one counſell and force, deliuer vp their authoritie and power ſecular to the deuotion and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Beaſt; and therefore the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit crowneth, not his heads, but his horns, ſaying, <hi>and vpon his hornes ten diadems.</hi> And concluding ſheweth (euen by his head attire) how far vnlike this Dragons High-prieſt of Rome was and ſhould be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23648:34"/> to the Lords High-prieſt of Ieruſalem, who (in ſtead of hauing his head-attire emblemiſhed with <hi>holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> as had his ſeruant <hi>Aaron)</hi> ſhould haue his head-peece beſlubbered with names of blaſphemie, <hi>and vpon his heads names of blaſphemie,</hi> whereof proofe is made in the ſixt verſe following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 2.</bibl>
                     <p> And the Beaſt which I ſaw was like to a Leopard, and his feet as a Beare, and his mouth as the mouth of a Lion, and the Dragon gaue him his own force, and his throne, and great power.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd foraſmuch as the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that this Beaſt ſhould be a far greater aduerſarie, and a far longer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter of the Church of God then any of the Monarchies which did ariſe afore him; he ſhapeth him an outſide anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his inward making, framing his parts of the moſt notable perſecuters that euer were; as concluding him for his extraordinary wickedneſſe <hi>the odde fellow,</hi> the totall ſumme and very accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:23648:35"/> of all other.</p>
               <p>And firſt for his preſumption, in extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe aboue the Prince of the Couenant, defouling his ſanctuary, deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating his ſacrifice, burning his ſtatutes, and inforcing the humble and meeke to the abnegation of the truth, by blood, fire, ſtrappadoes, and ſuch like exquiſite torments; the Spirit reſembleth him to his arch-type <hi>Antiochus</hi> deſcended from the Monarch of Greece, here (as in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel)</hi> deciphered by a Leopard, <hi>And I ſaw the Beaſt like a Leopard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in pride of life, in pomp and luxurie, the Spirit equalleth him with the Monarch of Perſia, and likeneth his arrogant and voluptuous gate to her ten Kings, here (as in <hi>Daniel)</hi> deciphered by a Beare, <hi>And his feet as of a Beare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the holy Ghoſt aſcribeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the proud, prophane and curſed mouth of the Mornarch of Babylon, in commanding the dwellers on earth (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of fire and fornace) to adore his golden idoll, which he had dedicated with cornets, ſackbuts, pſalteries, dulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers; which alſo the Spirit couereth (as <hi>Daniel</hi> doth) vnder the maske of a Lion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23648:35"/> 
                  <hi>And his mouth as the mouth of a Lion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſt of all, leſt happily he ſhould be leaſt beholding vnto his <hi>Bella Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> his deareſt Lady and miſtris of Rome, the holy Ghoſt ſaith, that the loue of his Patroneſſe the Dragon, was equal to the loue of a father towards his ſonne; for ſhe made him heire apparent and Lord of her Empire, ſubiecting all things to the feete of his cenſure, and confirming vnto him her throne and pallace of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran, with all the demefnes and glorie of Latium, as one of his owne alſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Latiumque relinquit Chriſto, &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muleam ſeptem cum collibus vrbem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 3.</bibl>
                     <p> And I ſaw one of his heads as it were ſlaine to death, but the wound of his death was cured, and all the earth was in admiration after the Beaſt.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd preſently after this great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was riſen, the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw ſuch a wound giuen to one of his heads, that the Beaſt was in eminent danger to be ſtricken downe againe, and ſlaine in the very egge; for ſo much
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:23648:36"/> the Spirit noteth in ſaying, <hi>And I ſaw one of his heads as it were ſlaine to death.</hi> For the better opening of which wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, we muſt not onely remember the Beaſt hath ſeuen heads, but we muſt alſo ſtep a little forward, and craue the aſſiſtance of the ſeuenteenth Chapter concerning the interpetation of the ſeuen heads, which ſaith, that <hi>the ſeuen heads are ſeuen hils, and they are alſo ſeuen kings;</hi> diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the true ſeate and ſituation of the citie of Rome, where Antichriſt ſhould keep his court and reſidence, by the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by the <hi>ſeuen kings</hi> the ſeuen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, which from the beginning of the world to this day haue ſucceſſiuely riſen and reigned ouer the earth, of which ſeuen, the Aſſyrian monarchie was the firſt, and the Romane the ſixt, of both which and their pue-f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llowes, is further reuealed in the ſeuenteenth Chapter following. Meane time we are here to obſerue, that as the holy Ghoſt doth therefore call his ſeuen heads by the name of ſeuen hils, becauſe the ſeate of Antichriſt ſhould be there, and not elſewhere placed and planted; ſo he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23648:36"/> them alſo <hi>ſeuen kings,</hi> becauſe the power of Antichriſt ſhould be an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie ſoueraigntie, compounded of ſuch ſpiritual and temporall claimes and iuriſdictions, as ſhould be equiualent in preſumption and prophanation, to all the tranſgreſſions of the ſeuen monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, which from the beginning hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto haue blaſphemed God and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his world.</p>
               <p>This foundation layd, doth ſhew, that this deadly wound giuen to one of his heads, which (as after appeareth) was the wound of a ſword, cannot be meant of any one of his heads after the firſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as they are hils, but as they are kings, and ſubiect to the ſword: and ſo by conſequence intendeth that one of his Imperiall heads, and namely his faire <hi>Adonis,</hi> his minion, lord and maſter of Rome, of whom he had ſo lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his breath and being, was ſo deadly wounded, as that the Beaſt himſelfe thereby was in great danger of extinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus hauing found the head, let vs look vnto the wound, that ſo we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcerne the great danger the Beaſt was in, deliuered in theſe words, <hi>as it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23648:37"/> were ſlaine to death.</hi> This deadly wound was giuen and driuen home to the head, by the ſword and incurſion of the Weſt Gothes, vnder the leading of <hi>Alaricus,</hi> who in the nineteenth yeare of <hi>Ceſar Honorius</hi> (of whom the Beaſt ſome foure yeares before had receiued his life) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred Italy, and gaue ſuch a deadly ſtroke vnto his powerfull pate, that for very feare the Beaſt lockt himſelfe vp in his den at Rauenna, while the enemy ript vp the ſtreetes of his Imperiall citie, filling them with famine, fire and ſword; which night of woe, or rather beginning of her wofull night, made an ancient friend of hers to bewaile and bind vp her deadly wounded head, with an old Ballad, after the tune of the burning of Troy:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quis cladem illius noctis, quis funera fando explicet?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut poſſit lachrimis aequare labores?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vrbs antiqua ruit multos dominata per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And hauing thus mortally wounded the head of the Beaſt (in the yeare of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation 410, and 1157 yeares after <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> had raiſed her walls with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood) proceeded to ſeize vpon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23648:37"/> the reſt of his dignities, hauocking and burning his chiefeſt honours, Latium, Campania, Apulia, Lucania, Calabria, where raging and deuiſing how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the power of the Empire for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and to ſpread his glorie ouer all, was by ſudden death blotted out, leauing his purpoſe and his armie royall to his wiues brother <hi>Ataulphus,</hi> who in like ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging haſte and fury returned to Rome, with an obſtinate intent and reſolution to obliterate the ancient name of Rome for euer, and to call her (in honour of his people) <hi>Gothia,</hi> or after his owne name <hi>Ataulpha;</hi> which counſell and purpoſe of his, had it been effected, ſir Antichriſt with all his primacies and ſupremacies had bid vs good night long ago; and all his gainfull enterludes of <hi>fides veſtra,</hi> and <hi>ne deficiat fides tua,</hi> and <hi>paſce oues,</hi> and <hi>tibi dabo claues,</hi> and <hi>quorum remiſeritis,</hi> with all his peſtilent painted traine of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, had been daſht in repeating, before euer they had come on ſtage. But to the end this recouery might be the plague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore of the earth, his deadly wound was healed, as the Spirit ſath, <hi>but the wound of his death was cured.</hi> For by the pleaſing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23648:38"/> prayers and ſubtill interceſſions of the Emperours ſiſter <hi>Placidia,</hi> whoſe beautie and bodie was eſpouſed to <hi>Ataulphus,</hi> for ſuch a time his furie was auerted, and his deſigne diſſolued, and himſelfe not only content at her amorous mediation to grant the citie of Rome pardon for her name, but alſo to leaue her eclipſed and dying honour, with all her Italy, to her ſtupified <hi>Honorius,</hi> who for feare was crept into his earth at Rauenna; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his ſpouſe <hi>Placidia</hi> with ſuch dower as himſelfe liſted, departed Italy, and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his tabernacle in France, then one of the chiefeſt prouinces of the Weſt Empire. And to this plaiſter the Spirit pointeth, in ſaying, <hi>but the wound of his death was cured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the holy Ghoſt foreſeeing the greatneſſe of the Beaſts power to come, which was yet but like vnto his ſin; and how that Satan his creator, who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him after the image and perfection of his owne wickedneſſe, ſhould affoord him ſuch letters commendatory to all the world, which naturally loueth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked inuentions, that the primacie of his Church and ſupremacie of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23648:38"/> ſhould ouerſpread all, and obtaine the praiſe of the earth; concludeth of him in this maner, <hi>And all the earth was in admiration of the Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 4</bibl>
                     <p> And they adored the Dragon which gaue power to the Beaſt; and they adored the Beaſt, ſaying, Who is like vnto the Beaſt, or who may warre with him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the children of misbeliefe aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the Dragon inhibited ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, decking his heatheniſh Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with names of holy and moſt holy titles, due to God alone; and they ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his execrable inuentions &amp; doctrines of diuels, worſhipping and diuifying his vncircumciſed traine of Ceſars, who had granted vnto Antichriſt ſuch power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable and vncontrollable iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which the Spirit anatomiſeth in theſe words, <hi>And they adored the Dragon which gaue power to the Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as in euill there is no meane, ſo theſe children of vnbeliefe went on, and beſtowed like titles and magnifications
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:23648:39"/> vpon this baſe and vile Antichriſt, who as the Prophet long ago foretold vs, by <note place="margin">Dan, 8.</note> policie ſhould proſper, and by peace de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy many, and ſtrike his adorers with ſuch a ſpirituall drunkenneſſe, that they ſhould not onely hang their gold, but their faith alſo vpon him, and verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that this vile and deſpicable Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, Delegate to <hi>Romulus,</hi> and Deputie to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> was Vicar to the Lamb, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to <hi>Peter.</hi> And thus reioycing ouer the error of their owne fantaſie, ſhould with <hi>Pigmalion</hi> admire and dote vpon the idoll of their owne caruing, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe ſhould adore and crie with that drunken King, <hi>Great art thou, O Bel, and in thee is no deceit:</hi> which occaſioneth the Spirit (in deteſtation of their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) to diſcloſe their ſhame, ſaying, <hi>And they adored the Beaſt, and ſaid, Who is like vnto the Beaſt, or who may warre with him?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 5.</bibl>
                     <p> And there was giuen to it a mouth, ſpeaking great things and blaſphemies, and power was giuen to it to worke fortie two moneth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:23648:39"/>
               <p>ANd as the Dragon did bequeath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Antichriſt his throne and his power in ſo large and ample maner, that his prieſtly key was in cutting and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſo like the Dragons ſword, that he that is wiſe may eaſily perceiue one craftsman made them both: ſo Satan the maſter and ſeducer of them both, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his Antichriſt with mouth and lips ſo like his owne, that whoſo heares him open, may truly ſay, <hi>quam ſimiles ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent labra lactucas,</hi> like lips like lettice; at which the Spirit pointeth, in ſaying, <hi>And there was giuen to it a mouth;</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it by an argument drawne from the fruit of his lips, <hi>ſpeaking great things and blaſphemies.</hi> Whereof the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> alſo inditeth him, foretelling that he ſhould open his execrable mouth, and ſpeake words againſt the moſt High; of which preſumptuous magniloquence the holy Ghoſt arraigneth him more particularly in the verſe following.</p>
               <p>And the Prophet alſo further repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that <hi>times and lawes and great power</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould be giuen into his hand, for a time and times, and the diuiding of a time;</hi> butting and bounding his tyrannous reigne and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23648:40"/> gouernment within the ſelfeſame circle and period, as here the Spirit doth, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother like propheticall conſtruction, ſaying, <hi>And power was giuen vnto it to work fortie two moneths.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 6.</bibl>
                     <p> And he opened his mouth vnto blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt God, to blaſpheme his name, and tabernacle, and thoſe which dwell in heauen.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN diſcouering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemous mouth of Antichriſt, the holy Ghoſt doth firſt and principally challenge him for preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to lay hand vpon his diuine and ſpirituall ſword, and to weare the name and title of Vicar to the Lamb, which ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, name and honour is onely due to the Spirit of the Lamb, the onely modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, comforter and commander of all the Lambs affaires and forces in heauen and in earth: and of this principal blaſphemy the Apoſtle condemneth him, in ſaying, <hi>And he opened his mouth vnto blaſphemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, the Lord challengeth him for preſuming to blaſpheme the word of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:23648:40"/> God, ſuperaduancing his whoriſh church aboue the diuine eternall teſtimonie, in and by which the Son of God is named and knowne; which contumely offered to his moſt holy word, the Lord accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as done to himſelfe and his moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name; for ſo the holy Ghoſt ſpeaking of that Lord that is faithfull and true, who with iuſtice iudgeth and fighteth, ſaith, that <hi>he was clothed with a garment ſprinkled with blood, and his name is called, The Word of God.</hi> The pourtraiture of which diuine and eſſentiall Word, is the ingrauen Scripture of his moſt holy and written word, and of this blaſphemie the Spirit inditeth him in theſe words, <hi>to blaſpheme his name.</hi> Leſſe maruell then if like a raging flood, downe bearing all before him, and ouerflowing all bankes of obedience towards God, he dare extol his curſed head aboue all that is called or named God, that is to ſay, all magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie, authoritie and power ſecular, which by Gods owne ordinance &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, is the onely true, liuely and immediate repreſentation of his owne perſon, iuſtice and gouernment here on earth, in and ouer all temporall cauſes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:23648:41"/> and perſons, as well Eccleſiaſtical as ciuil, of which high treaſon one Apoſtle alſo conuinceth him, 2. Theſſ. 2.</p>
               <p>No maruell then, if thus daring to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Lord of the houſe and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed Deputies, he dare blaſpheme the houſe of God, wherein his name is honored, curſing, reuiling and reputing it a houſe of ſchiſmatiques, heretiques, excommunincates; which blaſphemous and vndeſerued wrong, the holy Ghoſt layeth to his charge, in theſe words, <hi>and his tabernacle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſt of all, to ſhew that there is neither end nor meaſure in his blacke, preſumptuous and blaſphemous mouth, the Spirit further chargeth him with blaſpheming the Saints and ſeruants of God deceaſed, curſing, reuiling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning their doctrine, and yet bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, adoring &amp; erecting their ſhadows, ſepulchers and ſhrines, for mediators, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſors and reconciliators betweene God and the ſinner; like their curſed fore-elders the Iſraelites, who boaſted in the deſcent of their father <hi>Abraham,</hi> and yet blaſphemed the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> their father, of which blaſphemous
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:23648:41"/> and indicible contumely againſt the Son of God and his moſt holy Spirit, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle condemneth him, ſaying, <hi>And thoſe that dwell in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 7.</bibl>
                     <p> And it was giuen vnto him to make battell with the Saints, and to ouercome them: and power was giuen him vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery people, tribe, tongue, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd as after lightning followeth thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo after Antichriſts blaſphemie followeth his perſecution, as the Spirit teſtifieth, ſaying, <hi>And it was giuen him to bid battell to the Saints;</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> by way of expoſition alſo plainly ſetteth forth, ſaying, <hi>that he ſhould murther and conſume the Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the moſt high.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in further amplification of this his carnificious furie, the Spirit ſetteth forth the largeneſſe of his charter and commiſſion, by an exceſſiue loquution, foretelling vs that it ſhould be ſo large and general, that the fire of his prophane
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:23648:42"/> and ſycophantical keys ſhould take hold vpon euery nation and tribe; as if we pleaſe to caſt an eye vpon the times paſt, and conferre what he had, with what he hath, we ſhall eaſily diſcerne the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the holy Ghoſt in theſe words, <hi>And power was giuen him vpon euery Tribe, people, tongue and nation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 8.</bibl>
                     <p> And all that inhabite the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored it, whoſe names be not written in the booke of life, of the Lamb which was ſlaine from the beginning of the world.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt hauing in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of this Chapter diſcouered the birth, place, perſon, power, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and perſecution of Antichriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth now to the deſcription of his creatures and deuotaries, foretelling vs that they ſhould be ſuch onely (for vnto ſuch onely the particle <hi>all</hi> is here reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) as haue their portion and intereſt in this life, whoſe pietie, heauen, hope and glorie is here, and not elſewhere; which kind of out and ouercaſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the Spirit deſcribeth by a periphraſis
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:23648:42"/> moſt proper to their naturall and inbred diſpoſition, ſaying, they are <hi>thoſe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite the earth;</hi> therein diſcouering them as by a difference diuiſiue from ſuch as are the Lords pilgrims and ſtrangers on earth, hauing here no permanent abode or place of reſt, but ſeeking the things which are aboue, attend with patience the reuelation of a life and citie to come, not made with hands, where their Lord and their Redeemer liueth.</p>
               <p>And the Spirit proceeding ſheweth further, the ſupreme, hidden and vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuable reaſon why the adorers of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt thus defiled the ornaments of their calling, and why they loued lyes more then truth, the Beaſts penance more then Gods repentance, the Beaſts beliefe more then faith towards God; the Beaſts miſerable merits more then the fruits of the Spirit, hatred of ſin and loue of God, becauſe (as holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) <hi>they were not found in the Lords record, nor written with the righteous:</hi> for ſo much the Spirit vnfoldeth, ſaying, <hi>whoſe names be not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of life, of the Lamb which was ſlaine from the beginning of the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="verse">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:23648:43"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 9.</bibl>
                     <p> If any man haue an eare, let him heare.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Apoſtle hauing ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphered the nature and cariage of Antichriſt and his creatures, commeth now to diſcouer his reward and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which howſoeuer it tarry little or long, is of neceſſitie the reward of ſinne. But before the Spirit draweth out his ſword, it pleaſeth him in his accuſtomed mercie to awake his Church and her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and to moue them to a feare and reuerent attention, by a generall ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, proclaiming, <hi>If any man haue an care, let him heare.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 10.</bibl>
                     <p> He that ſhall leade into captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, goeth into captiuitie; and he that ſhall kill with the ſword, muſt be killed with the ſword: here is the patience and the faith of the Saints.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt in this verſe calleth Antichriſt to the Barre, and ſets him before the world, for the very <hi>he,</hi> on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:23648:43"/> the wrath of God and his heauie diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is to be executed. For he, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour and pretence of weeding out and rooting vp of heretiques, hath brought into the Church captiuitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, tortures and torments, to the horrible murther and ſlaughter of the Saints, when in ſuch caſes (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) he had neither precept nor exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the life of the Lamb or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſo to do; <hi>he,</hi> euen he, ſaith the Lord, is that partie, againſt whom this iuſt iudgement of taliation is laid vp in ſtore to be executed vpon him in that day, when the Lord ſhall bring againe the captiuitie of his Church, which for their ſins he hath giuen vp to the ſword and furie of the Beaſt, vntill ſhe haue borne the burthen of her ſhame, and (as the <note place="margin">Ezek. 39.</note> Prophet ſaith) renewed her beautie by her ſorrowes, and her glorie by her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; and then ſhall be fulfilled that which was ſpoken by the Prophet, <hi>Woe to thee that ſpoiledſt, and waſt not ſpoiled; and didſt deale wickedly, when they did not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>wickedly againſt thee: for when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoile, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled; and when thy ſinne is ended, thou ſhalt be rewarded;</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:23648:44"/> as here alſo the Spirit denounceth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that God ſhall ſcourge him with his owne inuentions, &amp; repay him home in his owne coine, ſaying, <hi>He that ſhall leade into captiuitie, ſhall go into captiuitie; and he that ſhall kill, ſhall be killed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in conſolation of the Spouſe, concludeth, that howſoeuer Antichriſt and his Delegates fooliſhly thought, by afflicting the Church, to deſtroy the Church, yet in her afflictions conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the very ſtrength and approbation of her children; for by the things they ſuffer, they learne obedience, &amp; through patience their faith is conſecrated, by the which they are perfected and made inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable of the promiſe of God: all which mercie and fauour is commended vnto them vnder the hand and ſeale of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by which their mad and drunken aduerſaries thought to conſume them, and like fooles did not conſider that as the workman doth ſquare the ſtone by ſtrokes, and as the ſnake doth caſt his old skin by paſſing through ſharp ſtones, ſo the Lord doth renew his Spouſe by ſtripes, and bruſheth off her old affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by paſſing her through the aſperitie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:23648:44"/> of tribulation; which holy and hidden conſideration, cauſeth the Spirit to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the ſufferings of the Saints ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to aſcribe vnto them the chiefeſt ſtayes and ſupportations of their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hope and calling, namely, <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>faith,</hi> ſaying, <hi>here is the patience and faith of the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 11.</bibl>
                     <p> And I ſaw another Beaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vp from the earth, and he had two hornes like the Lamb, but he ſpake like the Dragon.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt in the verſe forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hauing pronounced ſentence of death againſt Antichriſt, before he comes to the execution thereof, deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the arai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ment and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Clergie, that ſo they may be carted to the valley of Hinnom both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, whom the Lord here figureth vnder the name of the Beaſt, ſaying, <hi>And I ſaw another Beaſt;</hi> comprehending vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſingular number of <hi>one Beaſt,</hi> by a maner of ſpeech common to the holy Scriptures, the whole corporation and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:23648:45"/> vniuerſitie of falſe and lying teachers, who from the firſt Eremite, Hypocrite, Father, Prieſt, Monke, Frier, to the laſt trumping and vagabond Ieſuite, haue auouched the honour and adoration of Antichriſt. And is moſt aptly deciphered by their earthly, ſenſuall, and diuelliſh minds, in pointing to their country and place of extraction, whence and where ſuch weeds do grow, ſaying, <hi>comming vp from the earth.</hi> And commendeth their making and acquaintance to vs, by two exquiſite tokens, the one their perſon, the other their doctrine. Touching their ſhape and perſon, the Spirit ſaith, that it was in robe and exteriour appearance the very face and countenance of the Lamb, deckt and garniſhed with his owne two hornes, to wit, the Law and the Goſpel, wherew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>he Lamb doth ſaue and kill; for ſo the Spirit ſaith, <hi>And he had two hornes like the Lamb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as concerning the vſe and force of the hornes, the Spirit ſaith, they were therein ſo contrary to the Lamb, that when they did open, either to teach the Law or preach the Goſpell, they ſpake and taught like the Dragons Doctors,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:23648:45"/> and like the Prieſts of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> teaching and preaching vnto the children of the world, that they ought to worſhip the God of heauen, as the Dragons Prieſts had taught their fathers to worſhip the gods of the heathen. Which deteſtable propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of the worſhip of God, and prepoſterous adoration of his name, the Spirit detecteth, in ſaying, <hi>but he ſpake like the Dragon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 12.</bibl>
                     <p> And all the power of the firſt Beaſt he did in his ſight, and he made the earth and the inhabitants therein to adore the firſt Beaſt, whoſe wound of death was cured.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BY the power of the firſt Beaſt, is meant the purpoſe and plot of the Dragon for the vpholding and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their falſe and godleſſe religion, to the prophanation and extinction of the true worſhip and ſeruice of God; which forasmuch as he could not effect by force and open enmitie, I meane by the bloody perſecutions of his prophane and Ethnicke Ceſars, he did deuiſe to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:23648:46"/> put a new ſtring to his old bowe, and to worke it out by fraud and falſhood of friends, and thereupon perſwaded his Ethnicke Ceſars, that in policie it was the beſt to play Chriſtians, foraſmuch as the world was now ſo giuen, as <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> with all his idols muſt needs giue place to Chriſt, becauſe moſt voices went that way.</p>
               <p>And the better to bring the myſterie of iniquitie to paſſe, he cauſed his new Chriſtened Ceſars to ſet vp a race of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophanticall, high and princely Prieſts, who vnder colour of proctering the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Lamb, ſhould cunningly clap <hi>Iupiters</hi> coate vpon the Lambs back, and beſtow all the ceremonies and ritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and his idols vpon Chriſt; that ſo by turning <hi>Iupiters</hi> worſhip into Chriſtianiſme, he might turne the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God into Paganiſme and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and that ſo he might at the leaſt prophane and deſolate the true worſhip of the true God, whoſe maieſtie &amp; truth of deitie they could no way blemiſh.</p>
               <p>And for the better ſucceſſe in this their proiect, ſhould cauſe to be erected throughout all kingdomes and nations,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:23648:46"/> certaine Couents and ſwarmes of falſe, vngodly and proſtituted Clerks, who by auouching and maintaining againſt all comers, that Antichriſts name is <hi>Simon Peter;</hi> and that the ſupremacie his Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars and his Kings gaue him, is the very keyes of heauen and hell, which the Lamb committed to the diſpenſation of his Saints and ſeruants; and that the throne and ſeate of wickedneſſe, is <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire and Sea Apoſtolique; and that the execrable forme of <hi>Iupiters</hi> worſhip, wherein his Lords and Ceſars delighted, is the very true worſhip and ſeruice of God, which the Lamb and his Apoſtles deliuered.</p>
               <p>And by theſe miſts, legerdemains, and new editions of old idolatrie, ſhould eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh in the ſight of Antichriſt, the ſelfe ſame prophanation and deuout impietie which his anteceſſors the Ceſars ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently embraced; for ſo much the Spirit rippeth vp, in ſaying, <hi>And all the power of the firſt Beaſt he did in the ſight of Antichriſt:</hi> and thereby ſo ſtrongly deluded and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the children of diſobedience (moſt properly here, as elſewhere, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the name of <hi>the earth and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:23648:47"/> therein)</hi> that they loathed the ſacrifices of the God of heauen, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to worſhip as the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, &amp; choſe rather (as the Spirit ſaith) to adore the firſt Beaſt, that is to ſay, to worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of their fathers, as the Dragon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, iuſt after the preſcription of his Ceſars and maner of the heathen.</p>
               <p>And that we may the better diſcerne from whom thoſe Proctors of Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt borrowed this their abominable Church-ſeruice, the Spirit remembreth the repaired wound of their maſters cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors pate, mentioned in the third verſe, <hi>whoſe wound of death was cured.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 13.</bibl>
                     <p> And he did many ſignes, ſo that he made fire to come downe from heauen to the earth, in the ſight of men.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt hauing arraigned and condemned the Clergie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt touching their doctrine, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth further to detect their abomination and forgery, in ſeeking to confirme their falſe doctrine by lying ſignes and works of wonder; condemning therein firſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:23648:47"/> their vanitie; ſecondly their preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as nothing can be more vaine and vngodly, then to ſeeke by lying ſignes and wonders to confirme the doctrine of the Lamb and his ſeruants, which is all ſufficiently eſtabliſhed by their owne magnificent and diuine miracles, vnto which the Church of God vpon her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is enioyned to ſubſcribe: ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more preſumptuous and wicked, then to attempt by ſignes and wonders the confirmation of any other doctrine then that which the Lamb and his two witneſſes haue ſealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto vs, according to the ſtatute of God, Deut. 13.</p>
               <p>And though their ſignes were many, as the Spirit reporteth, ſaying, <hi>And he did many ſignes;</hi> yet were they but forgeries and lies, not wrought in truth &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but in falſhood &amp; fallacie, as our Lord himſelf and his ſeruant <hi>Paul</hi> foretold vs, Mat. 24. 2. Theſſ. 2. In which regard the holy Ghoſt ſquaring the miracles of theſe exorciſts after the rule of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which was in ſhew the Lambs, but in truth the diuels; calleth alſo their lying ſignes, heauenly fires, ſaying, <hi>ſo that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23648:48"/> he made fire to come downe from heauen to the earth, in the ſight of men:</hi> not that they were in deed and in truth ſo, but that they ſeemed ſo to be in the eyes of men, becauſe they were wrought by theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond exorciſts, vnder a pretended and colourable imitation of the name of the Lord Ieſus, who of all heauenly powers and fires is the true Lord and ſoueraigne commander; that ſo theſe Clerks of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt might be ſutable in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, that as their doctrine was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the truth of Chriſt, ſo their wonders might contrary the power of Chriſt, by a colourable imitation of the miracles of Chriſt, and might be a true and perfect deprauation of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 14.</bibl>
                     <p> And he ſeduced the inhabitants on the earth, through the ſignes which were giuen him to do in the ſight of the Beaſt, ſaying vnto them that dwell on the earth, that they ſhould make the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Beaſt which had the ſtroke of the ſword and liueth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the Spirit further diſcloſing the happie ſucceſſe of theſe vnhappie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:23648:48"/> brokers and ſlaues of Antichriſt touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their miſts and miracles, foretelleth vs, that as the firſt <hi>Elias</hi> by the miracles of heauenly fire did induce and draw the good vnto the feare of God, ſo theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſters of Antichriſt, by the lure of their falſe and lying fires, ſhould ſeduce and draw all dung-hill and earthly minded men from the feare of God, in ſuch ſure and deuoted ſort, as that they ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to make the picture and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Beaſts religion, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and erect ſuch a Chriſtianiſme, as ſhould in all points counterfeit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Paganiſme of the Dragon, attiring and decking <hi>Iupiters</hi> prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the holy and honorable names of God, Ieſus, Spirit, Scriptures, Church, Sacraments, Saints, &amp;c. like excellent Comedians who decke themſelues with Crownes, Scepters, purples, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of Kings, whenas indeed they are the baſeſt of the people. And as the Lord commanded his ſeruant <hi>Moſes</hi> to erect ſuch a Tabernacle of witneſſe here on earth, as ſhould be in all points after the Idea, modell and platforme of that diuine and eternall Tabernacle which he
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:23648:49"/> ſaw in the mount: ſo Antichriſt (Lord of miſrule) commanded his propudious Clergie to cauſe all people, nations and kingdomes to ſet vp ſuch a Chriſtianity as ſhould in all points anſwer the Idea, modell and platforme of that prophane and execrable heatheniſme wherewith he ſaw the Gentiles enamoured; and hereby ſo ſtrongly ſeduced the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants on earth, that they verily thought the myſterie of Iniquitie to be pure and vndefiled Chriſtianitie; and that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of deſolation, foreſpoken by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, is the onely true, ancient, Catholique and Apoſtolique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; teaching them that periſh by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting vnto lies, that they ought to worſhip God as the Gentiles did worſhip <hi>Iupiter;</hi> perſwading them that as the Gentiles had their <hi>Arae,</hi> ſo Chriſtians muſt haue their Altars; and as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then had their bloody ſacrifices, ſo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt haue their vnbloody ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and offer bread and wine to God, as the heathen did to <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Bacchus;</hi> and as the Pagans had their <hi>Poutifex ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus,</hi> ſo Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt haue their Pope; and as Ethnicks had their <hi>Sacerdotes,</hi> ſo
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:23648:49"/> muſt Chriſtians haue their Prieſts; and as the Gentiles had their gods and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes, ſo muſt Chriſtians haue their he Saints and ſhe Saints; and as the Dragon had his Pantheon, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his All Saints; and as the heathen had their idols, ſo Chriſtians muſt haue their images; and as the Pagans did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate their Temples to Idols, ſo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt dedicate their Churches to Saints; and as the Ethnicks had their ſupplications, ſo Chriſtians muſt haue their proceſſions; and as the Gentiles had their luſtrations, ſo Chriſtians muſt haue their holy water; and as the Dragon in his Church-ſeruice had his <hi>Cerei,</hi> ſo An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in his Church-ſeruice muſt haue candles; and as the Dragon had his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerra</hi> or <hi>Thuribles,</hi> ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Cenſors; and as the Dragon had his Nouendiall ſacrifices, ſo muſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt haue his Maſſes of <hi>Requiem;</hi> and as the Dragon had his Hecatombes, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Trentals; and as the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon had his Colledges <hi>Sodaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>Arvalium fratra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo muſt Antichriſt haue his Cloiſters of Monks and Friers; and as the Dragon had his Veſtals, ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:23648:50"/> Antichriſt muſt haue his Nunnes and Sanctimonials; and as the Dragon did celebrate the birth dayes of his <hi>Ceſars,</hi> ſo Antichriſt muſt ſolemnize the natiuitie of his Saints; and as the Dragon had his Annals, ſo muſt Antichriſt haue his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends; and as the Dragon had his ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Spectacles, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Iubilees; and as the Dragon had his Bacchanals, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Carnivals; and as the Dragon had his Lupanaries, ſo muſt Antichriſt haue his Stewes; and as the Dragon had his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſts; and as the Dragon had his <hi>Aſyla,</hi> ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and as the Dragon had his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies and Parentals, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Diriges and his <hi>de profundis;</hi> and as the Dragon had his <hi>comitia centariata,</hi> ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Councels oecumenicall; and as the Beaſt had his <hi>comitia curiata,</hi> ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Councels prouinciall; and as the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon did diuifie his <hi>Ceſars,</hi> ſo muſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt canonize his Saints; and as the Dragon enacted ciuill lawes, ſo Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt muſt enact Canon lawes; and as
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:23648:50"/> the Dragon had his Imperiall reſcripts, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his Decretall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles; and as the Dragon had his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunitial interceſſions, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue his vncontrollable interdictions; and as the Dragon had and vſed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, ſo Antichriſt muſt haue and vſe his excommunications; and as that Beaſt commanded his heathen to pleaſe their goddeſſe <hi>Iuno</hi> with <hi>cane vota libens,</hi> ſo this Beaſt commanded Chriſtians to pleaſe their God with vowes; and as the Dragon had his <hi>Triceps Hecate,</hi> ſo Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt muſt haue his triple <hi>tiara,</hi> to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his triple pretended iuriſdiction; and as the Dragon had his <hi>Hexaphoron,</hi> ſo muſt Antichriſt be carried vp &amp; downe; briefly, as the Dragons prieſts did teach the heathen to worſhip <hi>Iupiter</hi> as God, ſo Antichriſts Clergie muſt teach their Chriſtians to worſhip God as <hi>Iupiter;</hi> and looke what forme of religion, what maner of life the Dragon led, the ſame muſt Antichriſt in his perſon parallel &amp; maintaine.</p>
               <p>And to the end we may vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly diſcerne what and of whoſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, the Spirit
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:23648:51"/> remembreth now the third time his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured wound, which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here ſpeaking more plainly out, he calleth <hi>the ſtroke of a ſword;</hi> not that it was the onely ſtroke, (for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſwords did pierce the Dragon, as his had pierced many,) but the firſt ſtroke of a ſword, which from the beginning and riſing of the Dragons Empire and regiment by Ceſars, did remeaſure the fury of the ſword vpon his owne head &amp; chaire of ſtate, as the Spirit noteth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Which had the ſtroke of the ſword, and liueth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 15.</bibl>
                     <p> And it was giuen to him to giue ſpirit to the image of the Beaſt, and that the image of the Beaſt ſhould ſpeake, and ſhould make that whoſoeuer honored not the image of the Beaſt, be ſlaine.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd ſuch art and perſwaſible power was giuen to thoſe inchanters and apoſtates of Antichriſt, that they infuſed ſuch a quickning ſpirit, ſuch a life, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing animation into the Ethnicke dead and deſolate image of the Dragons reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by gilding it ouer with the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:23648:51"/> diuine and honorable names of God omnipotent, Chriſt Ieſus the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, his holy Spirit, his precious blood, his ſacred word, his bleſſed Sacraments, &amp;c. that they eaſily perſwaded the blear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyd world to think and beleeue, that the execrable forme and image of <hi>Iupiters</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, commanded by the Dragon and his Ceſars, was the very true worſhip and ſeruice of God, commanded by the Lamb and his ſeruants; and that the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Iupiter Olimpius</hi> which their Lord <hi>Epiphanes</hi> had ſet vp and placed in <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſanctorum,</hi> was the very Arke and propitiatory of God, ſet vp and erected by <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſeruant; and their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable myſticall Maſſe, the ſacrifice of an vnbloody Meſſias, made of bread of their owne baking (which their fathers the Patriarks, Prophets and Apoſtles neuer heard nor dreamed of) is a ſacrifice not Euchariſticall but propitiatory, and ſo allſufficient for the attonement and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of God vnto the ſinner, as if it were figured and ſealed in the precious blood of the Lord of the couenant; and that the horrible prophane and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupper of <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> is the very true,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:23648:52"/> holy and comfortable commemoration of the Lords loue in giuing his life for the children of the Church, and their thankfull communion and celebration of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And by theſe and ſuch like inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, theſe Proctors of Antichriſt ſo baffled and blinded the Princes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of their ſynagogues, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zealed them to authorize and erect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, executions and torments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch as refuſe to honour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the idol-ſeruice and deſolation of their <hi>Antiochus;</hi> and that all ſuch as doe but mutter againſt the magnificence of their Church and her worſhip, which all the world adoreth, ſhould be accounted as <hi>infoelix Lolium,</hi> weeds, Lollards, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, excommunicates, and ſonnes of death, to the admirable confirmation of the Spirits prediction in this place, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>it was giuen to him to giue ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the image of the Beaſt, that the image of the Beaſt ſhould ſpeake and make that whoſoeuer honored not the image of the Beaſt, be ſlaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="verse">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:23648:52"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 16.</bibl>
                     <p> And he ſhould make all, little and great, rich and poore, free and bond, to haue a character in their right hand or on their foreheads.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd the power of theſe proſtibulous Clerks was ſo catholique and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, that they cauſed all kingdomes and nations (figured here by a numera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their eſtates, conditions and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, <hi>little, great, rich, poore, bond, free,)</hi> to confederate and vnite themſelues by a reſolute and determinate purpoſe of beleeuing and liuing after the lawes and preſcriptions of Antichriſt; which league of voluntary and reſolute ſubiection, the Spirit calleth <hi>the character of the Beaſt:</hi> for as vnitie and loue in truth, and a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued purpoſe to liue after the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, is the character and cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of the Lamb; ſo vnitie, conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and banding againſt the truth, with reſolution to liue after the traditions of Antichriſt, is the creſt and character of the Beaſt. Which profeſſion of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was ſo ſtudiouſly embraced, and with ſuch ioy receiued of all the clients
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:23648:53"/> and creatures of Antichriſt, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſaith, they did no leſſe pride them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their errors and abominations, then in the wearing of their bracelets &amp; abillements, deliuering it in manner of ſpeech vſuall with holy Scripture, when it intendeth to expreſſe an ardent and hearty affection approued both by word and action, by practiſe and profeſſion, as Deut. 6. 8. and 11. 18. where the holy Ghoſt vſeth the ſelfeſame phraſe, <hi>in their right hand or on their foreheads.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 17.</bibl>
                     <p> And that no man may buy or ſell but he that hath the Character or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his name.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd in further proof that Antichriſt and his apoſtaticall Clergie ſhould driue the naile of their impietie home to the very head, the Spirit ſaith, that by them and meanes of their authoritie, it ſhould be enacted, that none ſhould trade or liue (for ſo much the inhibition of buying and ſelling doth inferre) but ſuch as acknowledge and adore the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:23648:53"/> royall, religion and diſcipline of the Beaſt and his holy Catholique Church (for ſo by a figuratiue kind of blaſphemie ſhe muſt be called) as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Antichriſt himſelfe, then na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Martin</hi> the fift, in his Bull directed to the Inquiſitors of hereticall prauitie (for ſo it pleaſeth him to terme the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth) <hi>nec domicilia habeant, nec larem foueant, nec contractus ineant, nec negotiationes &amp; mercatur as exerceant, nec humanitatis ſolatia cum Chriſti fidelibus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant, &amp;c.</hi> All which their dominering, rage or madneſſe, the holy Ghoſt by way of previſion moſt admirably epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth in theſe words, <hi>And that no man may buy or ſell,</hi> (no one excepted out of the King of Babylons decree) ſaue thoſe onely that carry his ſigning &amp; fleſhmark in their hands or hearts, as beaſts doe in their fells, meaning ſuch as vnder or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue boord, priuatly or in publique, are obſtinately &amp; reſolutely deuoted to liue and die as the Beaſt commandeth; which the Spirit vnfoldeth in ſaying, <hi>but he that hath the character,</hi> or are otherwiſe allied as it were by way of cognomination vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Antichriſt or his Church Catholique,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:23648:54"/> and are hereafter cleped Papiſts or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, reuealed in theſe words, <hi>or the name of the Beaſt;</hi> or laſt of all are found to adore within the very verge or liſts of his reigne and Empire Pontificial, here butted and bounded within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and comprehenſion of theſe words, <hi>or the number of his name,</hi> of which more at large in the verſe following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe 18.</bibl>
                     <p> Here is wiſedome; he that hath vnderſtanding, let him count the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Beaſt, for it is the number of a man, and his number is ſix hundred ſixtie ſix.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe holy Ghoſt intending to reueale in this verſe the ſecret counſell and purpoſe of God concerning the period and finall end of Antichriſt and his Church-dominion, prepareth his Reader to attention by a little ſhort preface, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that it is the diſcouery of a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie and point of high vnderſtanding, ſaying, <hi>here is wiſedome;</hi> wherein leſt we ſhould ouer-raſhly iudge (as many haue done) the Spirt maketh choiſe of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:23648:54"/> and addeth for a barre, not he that will, but he that can and hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, let him audite and count the number of the Beaſt; <hi>He that hath vnderſtanding, let him count the number of the Beaſt;</hi> whom l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt we ſhould imagine to be a ſpirit or other creature of ſtrange ſhape (as ſome haue vainly phantaſed) the Spirit calleth him <hi>a man,</hi> ſaying, <hi>for it is the number of a man,</hi> comprehending by a Synecdoche vnder the word <hi>man,</hi> a ſucceſſiue ſtate and kingdome of men, after the ſpeaking and ſtile of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: for ſo the Lord informed his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeake, <hi>Let my ſonne go,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> that is, let my people of Iſrael depart; and ſo in <hi>Daniel,</hi> vnder the forme and <note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> name of foure ſingular Beaſts, are deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned foure ſeuerall Monarchies, moſt of <note place="margin">Dan. 8.</note> them containing a long ſucceſſion of many Monarchs, <hi>The Ramme which thou ſaweſt are the Kings of the Medes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians:</hi> after which maner of ſpeaking, the Spirit ſpeaketh alſo in this place, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>a man</hi> preſenteth vnto vs the whole race and ſucceſſion of men of ſinne, whoſe totall ſumme is one Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the bounds and limits of whoſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:23648:55"/> dominion and tyrannie, the holy Ghoſt impaleth within the circuit of a certaine ſure prefixed period and determinate number of yeares, ſaying, <hi>and the number of him is ſix hundred ſixtie ſix.</hi> Wherein many, as well ancient as late writers (as in the reſt) they haue vainly imagined, that Antichriſt is one ſingular perſon, which muſt ſodainly ſtart vp, and after three ciuill yeares and a halfe depart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and that he muſt be by birth a Iew, and of the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> when notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe curſed ſcatterbags haue neither Tribe nor ſhadow of Tribe left amongſt them; and that he muſt reigne in Ieruſalem, of which Citie and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there is not any one ſtone left vpon another; and that he muſt kill <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> who are to appeare about the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lends of Greece; with diuers other ſuch legendary phantaſies, neuer meant nor ſent from God: ſo in this point alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the number of Antichriſt, they haue giuen vp an account ſo farre from the audite of truth, as nothing can be more. And as men that thought it worth the labour to find a knot in a ruſh, ſo by a conceited framing and anagramming
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:23648:55"/> of letters, they haue endeuoured to find out ſuch a name as by characters might expreſſe the number 666; and withall might ſomething ſquare either with the name, nature, blaſphemie, or reſidence of the Biſhops of Rome, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Remiith Adonikam, filius perditionis, &amp;c.</hi> whereunto alſo may be added the coniectures of <hi>Iohn Wickliff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Iohn Bale, Francis Iunius,</hi> men otherwiſe of good and worthy memory in the Church of God; as alſo the coniectures of others as worthy and honorable as they, that haue referred the number of 666 to the time of Antichriſts reuealing and yeare of riſing, when notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is a ſtrange voice, and not known to the eares of the Scriptures, for the word <hi>number</hi> to be vſed for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and riſing of any terme of time li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and predicted by the Prophets, but onely for the end, period, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination thereof.</p>
               <p>But if it were lawfull to ſmile in ſo graue an inquiſition, amongſt all phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall charmes and cabaliſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures vpon this word <hi>number,</hi> there is
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:23648:56"/> none more ridiculous then that which moſt pleaſeth out Rhetoricall Rhemiſts, who by a rare ſupputation of characters, haue as roundly found out the Beaſts number, as the Sodomites did the doores of <hi>Lot,</hi> in the name <hi>Luderus,</hi> which in the Almain tongue is the name of <hi>Luther:</hi> and although we are ſure, they cannot ſo much as thinke vpon the poore Frier <hi>Luther,</hi> but for very feare they ſtinke all the world ouer; yet this deuice ſo tickleth the Clergie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that they pretend to laugh for ioy. But as for their prefixed time of three naturall or ciuil yeares and a halfe (which they allot to the reigne and rage of their Antichriſt) it doth ſo vneuenly ſquare with <hi>Luther</hi> or Lutherans continuance, that theſe miſerable Serdonians are faine to eate their word, and to endure the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh world to laugh at them, whiles as dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they faine would ſeeme to laugh at it. But to leaue theſe curſed leaders of the curſed blind, and returne againe to thoſe that haue thought to calculate &amp; find out the myſtery of Antichriſts num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 666, in a word, we ſay, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and erre, not knowing the power
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:23648:56"/> and conſtruction of the Scripture. For firſt, by the word <hi>name,</hi> deliuered in the former verſe, in theſe words, <hi>or the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his name,</hi> is meant the very exiſtence and perſon of the man of ſinne, by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of ſpeech common to holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as Acts 1. 15. Apoc. 3. 4. and 11. 13. where (by an Hebraiſme) <hi>names</hi> ſignifie <hi>men,</hi> and are conuerted with the parties and perſons themſelues, as the name of God in holy Scripture is often taken for God himſelfe: and therefore as in the former verſe the Scripture calleth it <hi>the number of his name,</hi> ſo in this verſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it <hi>the number of a man,</hi> vnderſtanding by <hi>a man</hi> (as is afore ſaid) the total ſumme of that ſucceſſion of beaſtly men, which make and conſtitute the exiſtence and perſon of one Antichriſt: and by the word <hi>number,</hi> is meant the fatall end and finall determination of their reigne and gouernment; for ſo the finger of God ſpeaketh to <hi>Baltazar, God hath numbred thy kingdome,</hi> that is, God hath ended and finiſhed the dayes of thy kingdome: ſo that <hi>the number of his name,</hi> or <hi>the number of the man,</hi> is nothing elſe but the period and finall determination of the vſurped
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:23648:57"/> tyrannie and domination of Antichriſt; which the Lamb the Lord and preſeruer of Iſrael, for the glorie of his name, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of his Church, and confuſion of her foes, with a mighty and outſtretched arme ſhall bring to paſſe in the yeare which ſhal be 666.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as the egge of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme was laid in the dayes of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the firſt, ſucceſſor to <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the firſt alſo of that name, in the yeare of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation 406, as is before declared; and that by expreſſe commiſſion there was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore granted to the Beaſt, his heires and ſucceſſors 1260 yeares, for the hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, foſtering and perfecting this child of perdition and myſtery of iniquitie, which being added to 406, by rule of true audite muſt needs verifie this admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable iudgement, which the Spirit of God hath here denounced and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make good vpon him in the yeare which ſhall be 1666. In which account and diſcouery of his end, the holy Ghoſt of purpoſe leaueth out the millenarie number, as not onely knowne perfect and immutable (for that theſe vile and euill dayes ſhall not exceed more thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:23648:57"/> then one) but as reſpecting alſo the common vſe of all nations, as well Hebrewes as Gentiles, who in their ſtiles (for breuitie ſake) do no leſſe often ſpeak <note place="margin">Vide Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darium He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raieum Sebaſtianl Munſteri.</note> and write by the imperfect number, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the millenary, then after the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect adding the millenary, as <hi>Munſter</hi> well obſerueth. And in that yeare my Lord of Rome ſhall lay downe his proud waues; and although he fortifie neuer ſo ſtrong, and lay his foundation as low as hell, and build his turrets as high as heauen, and place his Miter aboue the ſtarres, yet in that day he ſhall die the death of the vncircumciſed, and periſh like the Amorite, whoſe fruit is deſtroyed from aboue, and roote from beneath; and the multitude of his offences ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the multitude of his forces; and it ſhall be more poſſible for him and eaſie vnto him to weigh the fire, or meaſure the wind, or call againe the day that is paſt, or recouer the verdure of the withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red graſſe, (as a holy one ſaith) then to auoide this counſell and decree of his downfall here determined by the Spirit againſt him, ſaying, <hi>and the number of him is</hi> 666. And then all kingdomes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:23648:58"/> ſhall ſee the eternitie of that eternall citie (as one of her owne calleth it) and the immortalitie of her ſoule, meaning the ſoueraigne power and ſupremacie of her Ceſars and high Prieſts, to wither, die, and forſake the earth for euer: and as Babylon her mother left vnto her the inheritance of her pride and prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo ſhall ſhe alſo leaue vnto her the heritage of her death and iudgements: for as her glorie hath been great, ſo ſhall her diſhonour, when all her excellencie ſhall be tranſlated into ſhame and ſorow.</p>
               <p>Now therefore as King <hi>Baltaſher</hi> cried aloud when he ſaw the hand-writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that they ſhould bring the Caldeans, Aſtrologians and Inchanters to reade and interpret; ſo thou that once and long before our dayes haſt been dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by lawes of all nations a power ſo ſoueraigne &amp; holy, call now about thee thy Councell and thy Clergie (who call themſelues Good men, learned and wiſe, whoſe onely grace is to loue antiquitie, grauitie, wiſedome and conſtancie,) call them I ſay, cloath them with purple and chain them with gold, yet ſhall they not deliuer thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this iudgement to come;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:23648:58"/> but as the mill-ſtone which the mightie Angell took and caſt into the ſea, which may not riſe and floate againe, with ſuch violence thou and thy Church in that houre ſhall be throwne downe, and ſhall be found no more. And all ſuch Kings on earth, or rather Kings of earth, whoſe loue thou haſt ſtolen, to the loſſe of their ſoules, that haue liued in drunkenneſſe, delights and wantonneſſe with thee, ſhal weep and waile for thee (as for their firſt borne) when they ſhall ſee the ſmoake of thy torments aſcend, and the apples which thy ſoule luſted after, to depart from thee, and no man to buy thy traſn and commodities any more; for that God which iudgeth thee is a ſtrong Lord, and thy deriſion ſhall be the ioy and Alleluia of Sion.</p>
               <p>But her faire and halcyon day may not long endure, before the Lord (that with iuſtice iudgeth and fighteth) ſhall come in the clouds of heauen, to render vnto euery man according to the ways where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his heart hath walked, as more directly is reuealed in the 20 Chapter following. But as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the day &amp; houre of the coming of that Lord, who for the glorie
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:23648:59"/> of his name ſhall bring theſe things to paſſe, it is faſt ſealed vp in the treaſurie of God, far beyond the aime of all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in earth, or Angels in heauen; and yet his beloued ſeruant <hi>Daniel</hi> is bold in ſpirit, and layeth downe the yeare to be the fiue and fortith yeare (according to his Caldaicall ſupputation) after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and extermination of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that it may be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophet, <hi>Verily the Lord of hoaſts will doe nothing, but he reuealeth his ſecrets vnto his ſeruants the Prophets.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Amos 3.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23648:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
